<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-US" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:/jason/feed</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/jason"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://world.hey.com/jason/feed.atom"/>
  <title>Jason Fried</title>
  <updated>2024-07-12T22:10:36Z</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/38379</id>
    <published>2024-07-12T21:55:00Z</published>
    <updated>2024-07-12T22:10:36Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/jason/achieving-optionality-56634dd3"/>
    <title>Achieving optionality</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;It took me a while to fully realize the value of something my company achieved years ago, and continues to savor today. It’s one of our greatest quiet advantages, full stop.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It’s not something you hear much about in business circles. In fact, I can’t remember the last time I heard anyone spend much time on the topic, or even bring it up in conversation, on a conference stage, or behind a podcast mic.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;There is, however, lots of discussion about achievement in business. A company can achieve product market fit, operational efficiency, influence, revenue goals, or, ultimately — and hopefully — profitability.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But I’m not taking about those things. Those are the obvious things, the common talking points. And to those you can add the vanity metrics of achievement — social media followers, traffic, views, impressions, open rates, press mentions, gross this or gross that.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;All those are what they are, but they aren’t where it’s at.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;What I’m talking about is optionality. Achieving optionality is where it’s at.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Optionality is a hearty mix of profit margin, small size, independence, attitude, and freedom. You’ve got to have all of it to have optionality.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;If a board is calling the shots, you don’t have much optionality. If your margins are thin, or non-existent, you don’t have much optionality. If the public owns a piece, you don’t have much optionality. If you rely on investment to pay the bills, you don't have much optionality. If you’re too big to change direction quickly, you don’t have much optionality. And if you’re afraid to speak your mind and stake your point of view, you don’t have much optionality.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Optionality lets you do things no one would give you permission to do. It lets you write excellent software and give it away for free if you choose. It lets you do things that don’t make sense in the current climate, but will long-term. It lets you be early while eventually catches up.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Optionality is ecstasy. It’s making it up as you go, without making excuses. It’s openly changing your mind without having to save face. Optionality is equanimity, the corporate equivalent of enlightenment.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;So, entrepreneurs, ditch the bullshit. Abandon growth-at-all-costs. Reject conventional metrics. Scorn hollow acceptance. Instead, hunt for optionality. It's freedom. It's power. It's everything you crave, wrapped in a single, potent package. Chase it relentlessly. And when you get it, don’t let go.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;-Jason&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>Jason Fried</name>
      <email>jason@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/38349</id>
    <published>2024-07-11T18:03:52Z</published>
    <updated>2024-07-11T18:03:52Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/jason/directional-decisions-22bcd41c"/>
    <title>Directional decisions</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;In the course of building products, you’ll make a thousand common decisions, but only a handful of directional decisions.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;While a common decision may alter a specific feature, design, or implementation, a directional decision remaps the fundamental trajectory of the entire product.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Make a directional decision and you’re now pointed this way or that way. Make a directional decision and you either shut something off or open something up. Make a directional decision and you’ll get a hundred no’s for the price of one.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Let’s look at a specific directional decision we made for &lt;a href="https://once.com/writebook"&gt;Writebook&lt;/a&gt;, our latest product.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Writebook is remarkably simple software that lets you publish text and pictures in a simple, browsable online book format.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Books are written and published. This presents an opportunity to make a directional decision: Is Writebook a writing tool or a publishing tool? Or both?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;At one point, we treated the publishing side and the writing side as equals. Both are involved in getting a book online. Seems reasonable, right?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Reasonable isn’t the measure, though. It’s easy to say something should do everything well because saying something is easy doesn’t involve any work, or require any tradeoffs. But building products is all about tradeoffs. When there are no tradeoffs in the conversation you’re having, you know you aren’t building, you’re just talking. But it was time to build.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But what’s the epicenter of Writebook? What’s the thing you can do easily with Writebook that was a lot harder without Writebook? Essentially, what does Writebook exist to do? What did the current world look like without Writebook?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;You can write books in a thousand tools in a thousand places. But instantly publishing a book in a simple web-friendly format is really hard. It generally involves a lot of custom work, or a complex CMS system, or bending some blogging platform into a pretzel just to unsatisfyingly make it sorta kinda create books instead of blogs.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;And since Writebook supports Markdown, you can easily write in a simple text editor and then copy and paste the finished text into Writebook when you’re ready. The place to write isn’t what’s lacking out there. The place to publish is.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;So we made a directional decision: Writebook was a publishing tool. You could obviously still write in it — we even designed a new Markdown editor to make basic formatting easier. But, our overall directional deciding Writebook was about publishing rather than writing allowed us to say no to dozens of days of additional work and sidestep piles of additional complexity.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But how did that decision come to be? Why did it happen? When did it happen?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Well, before we settled on the publishing angle, we went down the “writing and publishing are equals” path. Part of that project involved building a system to track diffs so an author (or multiple) could track changes, additions, and subtractions. Writing software usually has this sort of thing, so if we were making writing software it felt like basic table stakes.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It was during a design review that it hit me. This is fucking complicated and unnecessary. It’ll work, but it’s not actually useful. And, further, trying to build a multiple-author change tracking system to our standards is going to distract us from the more important, core differentiation work we have to do on the publishing side.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;So I wrote up my thoughts and posted it to the Writebook project in Basecamp. Here is that post in full: &lt;a href="https://public.3.basecamp.com/p/4SfGJ2wQNXdUArbxf7FjDouz"&gt;https://public.3.basecamp.com/p/4SfGJ2wQNXdUArbxf7FjDouz&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;  &lt;figure class="attachment attachment--preview attachment--lightboxable attachment--png"&gt;
      &lt;a download="full-basecamp-thread.png" title="Download full-basecamp-thread.png" data-click-proxy-target="lightbox_link_blob_1731093396" href="https://world.hey.com/jason/22bcd41c/blobs/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaHNLd2VVWXk1biIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoiYmxvYl9pZCJ9fQ==--ab405854e71799379a613e7a594b143da66b57ef/full-basecamp-thread.png?disposition=attachment"&gt;
        &lt;img src="https://world.hey.com/jason/22bcd41c/representations/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaHNLd2VVWXk1biIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoiYmxvYl9pZCJ9fQ==--ab405854e71799379a613e7a594b143da66b57ef/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaDdDam9MWm05eWJXRjBTU0lJY0c1bkJqb0dSVlE2RkhKbGMybDZaVjkwYjE5c2FXMXBkRnNIYVFLQUIya0NBQVU2REhGMVlXeHBkSGxwU3pvTGJHOWhaR1Z5ZXdZNkNYQmhaMlV3T2cxamIyRnNaWE5qWlZRPSIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoidmFyaWF0aW9uIn19--946116ea0c454412635aa7309bd9472bf633014c/full-basecamp-thread.png" alt="full-basecamp-thread.png" srcset="https://world.hey.com/jason/22bcd41c/representations/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaHNLd2VVWXk1biIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoiYmxvYl9pZCJ9fQ==--ab405854e71799379a613e7a594b143da66b57ef/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaDdDam9MWm05eWJXRjBTU0lJY0c1bkJqb0dSVlE2RkhKbGMybDZaVjkwYjE5c2FXMXBkRnNIYVFJQUQya0NBQW82REhGMVlXeHBkSGxwUVRvTGJHOWhaR1Z5ZXdZNkNYQmhaMlV3T2cxamIyRnNaWE5qWlZRPSIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoidmFyaWF0aW9uIn19--8c0bbbd8bfe72a73b222ec1c20265f8631973dc9/full-basecamp-thread.png 2x, https://world.hey.com/jason/22bcd41c/representations/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaHNLd2VVWXk1biIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoiYmxvYl9pZCJ9fQ==--ab405854e71799379a613e7a594b143da66b57ef/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaDdDam9MWm05eWJXRjBTU0lJY0c1bkJqb0dSVlE2RkhKbGMybDZaVjkwYjE5c2FXMXBkRnNIYVFLQUZta0NBQTg2REhGMVlXeHBkSGxwUERvTGJHOWhaR1Z5ZXdZNkNYQmhaMlV3T2cxamIyRnNaWE5qWlZRPSIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoidmFyaWF0aW9uIn19--d2fed6b5089e475a3013538949ec7f311ac6e345/full-basecamp-thread.png 3x" decoding="async" loading="lazy"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I concluded with:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;Workbook is a final publishing platform, it's not a collaborative editing environment. What we're solving for is easily getting a book up online, in in various formats, in the simplest, quickest, more comprehensive way. If you want comprehensive collaborative editing and change tracking, write it elsewhere and, when it's done, pop it in here to publish.&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;We ended up keeping a very minimal version of writing history in place as a backstop for major mistakes (“Oh shit, I deleted the whole thing by accident”), but in the final version of Writebook there’s no formal track changes feature, no colored diffs, and no focus on the collaborative writing process.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Writebook is simply a final publishing platform first and foremost. You can write and edit in it, but it’s bare bones and basic — which is fine almost all of the time anyway.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;And guess what? Writebook has been out for a few weeks now and tracking changes or sophisticated collaborative editing tools or features has barely been requested. I’m glad we explored it early on, but even more glad we dropped it in the end. Publishing was the right direction.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;-Jason&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>Jason Fried</name>
      <email>jason@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/38143</id>
    <published>2024-07-03T18:46:36Z</published>
    <updated>2024-07-03T19:03:03Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/jason/introducing-writebook-e217cae3"/>
    <title>Introducing Writebook</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;You know, it's really easy to publish short form content on a variety of social platforms. And individual blog posts on a number of other platforms. These are solved problems.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But it's surprisingly challenging to publish books on the web in nice, cohesive, tight, easy-to-navigate HTML format. A collection of 20 essays can be a book. Or a company's handbook can be a book. Or an actual book like Shape Up can be a book.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But usually you have to make a custom web site, or stretch to use a blog publishing/CMS tool to kinda-sorta squish separate posts together into a packaged whole. It's really not ideal. We know — we've published a variety of books online, and we've had to go the custom route each time.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Having to go the custom route for something that should be fundamentally simple is a red flag. And an opportunity. It really shouldn't be this hard.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;So we did something about it. Introducing Writebook. It's a dead simple platform to publish web-based books. They have covers, they can have title pages, they can have picture pages, and they can have text pages. Each book gets its own URL, and navigating and keeping track of your progress is all built right in.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Writebook isn't a service — it's software you download and install on your own server. We've made it incredibly easy to get going — it just takes a few minutes. Even non-technical folks can get it all set up. We'll email you a single command you paste into a terminal and it takes care of the rest. No maintenance required either, it takes care of itself, auto-updates, etc.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Writebook also comes with all the Rails code so you can see how it's built, modify it for your own use, and learn how applications like this are made.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;And how much for all this? Absolutely nothing. Writebook is FREE.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Writebook is our love letter to truly independent, zero-cost web publishing on the open web. No gatekeepers, no publisher required. Just you and your words for the world.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Learn more and get it here:&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href="http://once.com/writebook"&gt;http://once.com/writebook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;-Jason&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>Jason Fried</name>
      <email>jason@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/38040</id>
    <published>2024-06-28T18:18:17Z</published>
    <updated>2024-06-28T18:31:26Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/jason/sometimes-it-s-better-sometimes-it-s-worse-c601264c"/>
    <title>Sometimes it's better, sometimes it's worse</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;Failure is a word worth eliminating from your vocabulary.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;There’s no reason to think about things that didn’t work out as failures.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Yet, it’s especially pervasive in entrepreneurial circles. It’s almost as if failure has been fetishized. Nearly worshipped as a right of passage, a prerequisite, a required step on the way.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I’m not here to say everything works out. Most things don’t. Plenty of things I’ve poured time and attention into never went anywhere. It can be disappointing. And, depending on what went into it, and what you're left with, it can put you in a perilous spot.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But, for your own good, it’s best to relativize things like this — especially when the odds are perpetually, and naturally, stacked against you.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Collecting losses, and becoming a connoisseur of catastrophe, won’t help you get a win next time around.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;So, what instead?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;For me, it’s a simple shift. I’ve always just felt that some stuff works out better than other stuff. I think that’s the healthiest way to think about it. Just a drop of relative recognition is all it deserves.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I also don’t think you’ll find that many lessons looking back on what didn’t work. You probably don’t really know why it didn’t work anyway. It feels good to imagine you do, but there isn’t a long history of people doing the same thing again, swapping this one wrong thing for another presumed right thing, and turning it all around. But if it was so easy to see what went wrong on reflection, shouldn’t there be turnaround stories everywhere you look?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;More likely, it a swirling confluence of decisions, ideas, events, timing, conditions, and serendipity that drove it off the map.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It’s easy to reflect comfortably on convenient assumptions about the past, but real reasons happen in present conditions.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;So yeah, some stuff works out better than others. That means some stuff doesn’t work at all. But it’s not a failure, and it doesn’t need a name. It just didn’t pan out as you hoped. Move on, look forward, learn by doing and not reviewing, and get on with it.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Next time isn’t that time again, it’s a time that never happened before.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;-Jason&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>Jason Fried</name>
      <email>jason@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/37996</id>
    <published>2024-06-26T19:03:30Z</published>
    <updated>2024-06-26T19:05:42Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/jason/software-defaults-15955a8e"/>
    <title>Software defaults</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;One of my favorite things about designing software is designing the defaults.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The defaults define the experience for everyone out of the box. And, therefore, for most people in perpetuity. Convention over configuration rules the day. To me, everything it could possibly do is less interesting than what it does right now, factory fresh.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;At 37signals we call this The Golden Path and we discuss it often. If a customer followed our lead, stayed in the grooves, and did exactly as the software suggested, what would that experience be like? That's the one nearly everyone will have, so making it great is our top priority.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Certainly some will take the path least traveled. Others will head to whatever gear icon they can find and start turning the dials and pulling the levers. And then there are those who enjoy figuring out how to break things by imagining every exception or edge case, and seeing how the app handles it. It's great to have these customers too! But they aren't the ones that pay the bills.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Most buy something they just want to work. Configuration is a drag, not a desire. Setting something up brings them down. They just want their struggle out of the way, and choosing and buying the thing was the majority of the work they signed up for. The rest should just glide.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Defaults aren't just about nailing The Golden Path, it's also about choosing one. What experience do we want people to have? What opinions do we want to carve into the product? It's not just what we're trying to do, it's what we're trying to say.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;So if you really want to know what a company thinks about their product, their customer, and the experience they imagine is the best one, just roll with the stock product. Don't mess with it, use it as is. That's the best way to know what something's really like, what was intended, and experience a pure point of view.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;-Jason&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>Jason Fried</name>
      <email>jason@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/37932</id>
    <published>2024-06-22T23:26:22Z</published>
    <updated>2024-06-23T05:16:09Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/jason/thoughts-on-the-search-for-life-7bb9c6e6"/>
    <title>Thoughts on the search for life</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;Just listened to Lex Fridman and Sara Walker talk about the origins of life, the search for life, what is life, etc. It was a wonderfully refreshing, nourishing conversation.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wwhTfyX9J34"&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=wwhTfyX9J34&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It made me want to spill out some random thoughts on the subject. I’m unqualified, but I’m curious.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Our search for life off this planet is inherently primitive. We search for life based on our definitions, using instruments designed to detect what we already know. And who can blame us? It would be impossible to look for what we wouldn’t recognize in a way that we can’t realize.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It wasn’t until the 17th century that we even discovered microbial life. And microbial life is the most plentiful life on earth, far surpassing the biomass of plant, animal, and fungal life combined. There’s more of it than anything, and we’ve always been living among it, yet we didn’t know it was here.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But it wasn’t just that. Since we share a common ancestor with microbial life, we didn’t find new life, we found an earlier version of who we were.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Imagine a microbe evolving so much intelligence that it forgot where it came from, only to invent instruments billions of years later to find itself again. That’s what happened. How beautiful is that?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Maybe it will happen again. If we find life elsewhere, we might be discovering a more advanced version of ourselves. Or if life finds us, it might rediscover its primitive origins. If we can forget and lose our history once, why couldn't we forget and lose our future again?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It makes me think about what other forms life could take. And how we might never be able to detect it.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Let’s imagine that thoughts were a form of life. They feel like it. They mate, they multiply, they evolve, they consume us, they drive us, they make us move, they seem to be born, they seem to die. They seem to have their own agency, appearing in your mind whether welcome or not.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But you can't see thoughts. You don't even know a thought exists until you, or someone else, has it. Maybe thoughts are location-based, waiting in every place. To discover one, you can’t look for it. Rather, you  have to be where it is.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Imagine what it would be like to stand on Mars, looking back at Earth. But if you were actually there, you’d almost certainly have a thought you couldn’t have here. Insights incompatible with any earthly experience. Questions that couldn’t be contemplated without standing on Martian sand.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;From Mars, the Earth is mirror. From Earth, Mars is a mirror. Both mirrors, but each perspective reflecting entirely different thoughts. You can’t see the same view or have the same thought from the other place. You must be there to meet thoughts living there.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Maybe thoughts don't exist in time and space but in mind and place. This specific mind, in that specific place.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Then imagine trying to look for thoughts with our instruments and techniques. Nothing would register. Trillions of thoughts unnoticed, unaware. They can’t be measured, they can only be experienced. How could we ever find them without having them, without being there, without being them?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;We search for life as if it's something to be found. But perhaps there's something even more alive, beyond our current understanding.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;-Jason&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>Jason Fried</name>
      <email>jason@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/37390</id>
    <published>2024-05-28T23:05:19Z</published>
    <updated>2024-05-28T23:25:08Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/jason/lighten-your-grip-724c37a3"/>
    <title>Lighten your grip</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;I recently took up drumming. Again.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;One of the first things you realize, other than you suck, is that you’re gripping the sticks too hard.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;A tight grip denies certain degrees of freedom, limits subtlety, and ups the fatigue factor. Plus you give up the gift of bounce the drum heads happily offer. It’s like you’re constantly paying interest vs. borrowing for free.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I had the same experience when learning to play guitar. It’s like I was trying to choke the neck to death.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Clenching the neck makes every change a three step process: Release, move, and clamp down again. It’s slower, it’s harder, and it’s a lot less natural than a flowing motion up and down the neck, pausing to play, rather than stopping.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It’s a curious thing. We tend to hold on too tightly early on. It seems to be part of learning just about anything. It's in the nature of starting. When you don’t know what you’re doing, at least you know how to squeeze.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But then, you discover that making progress requires you to release a little, to lighten up on your grip.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;A big part of what you see when you watch someone great is what you don’t see. Tension is notably absent. Instead, a certain ease, a gentle fluidity. A grace, not a grind.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;This shows up everywhere. To let go is to get somewhere.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;-Jason&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;——&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;em&gt;A great tip via Jack Nicklaus: &amp;quot;He said hold the golf club like you would hold a bird. Tight enough it won’t fly away but not so tight you’d hurt it.&amp;quot; (via &lt;a href="https://x.com/kadavy/status/1795594760989909128"&gt;https://x.com/kadavy/status/1795594760989909128&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>Jason Fried</name>
      <email>jason@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/37031</id>
    <published>2024-05-10T18:07:03Z</published>
    <updated>2024-05-10T18:16:29Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/jason/separation-162a4b53"/>
    <title>Separation</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;In my experience, a key skill to develop is the ability to separate one thing from another. To prevent the small from becoming the all.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Take a policy, for example. Could be a government, or a school, or a home owner’s association, or something at work. Whatever it is, you don’t like it. You don’t agree, you don’t like the decision maker, you don’t like how it was enacted, pick a reason, it doesn’t matter which. When you don’t like something, there’s a tendency for that one thing to become everything.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Now you don’t like the whole government, Or the whole school. Or the whole association. Or the whole company. Or, if it’s a specific problem with a product, then the whole product is a problem.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Is it? Or is it you?&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Not you as in you did the thing, but you dissolving the membranes, turning a complex organism back into a single cell. It’s psychologically simpler to cast an opinion collectively than it is specifically, but in the end, that easy street often leads to a dead end.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;It’s easy to feel “I’m pissed”, but really, just part of you is pissed. At that same time, another part of you loves your partner, another part of you is excited about the trip you’re about to take, another part of you is nervous awaiting the results of a recent blood draw, another part of you is focused on the current task, another part is hungry for lunch. We contain multitudes, and recognizing that you’re a thousand things rather than your most obvious emotion is a step towards maturity.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Take something your friend said recently. You kinda can’t believe they said it. Shocked, even. They’re on that side? They took that take? Ok, let’s say they did. Now, do you let it bleed into everything else you think about them? You could, but I’d suggest that’s your problem, not theirs. What about the other things about them? They’re your friend, after all. You got here somehow, and it wasn’t because of the things you didn’t like about them. There’s a good chance all the good stuff is still the good stuff. The relationship has more depth now. In this context, complexity is a gift.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Now replace friend with government or group or company or product or organization.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Developing the ability to tease things apart helps you compartmentalize the less desirable from the more desirable, and see the whole map, with all its separate states of like and dislike, favorable and unfavorable. There’s a very good chance that when you do that, you’ll like a lot more than you despise.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Kids know this, then it seems they — we — forget it. Kids like their food separated. Don’t let the blueberries touch — CONTAMINATE! — the chips. Don’t let the carrots graze the sandwich. Don’t let the cookies touch the cheese. This way they can HATE the carrots, but love their lunch. In an absurd way, it seems like the healthy approach.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Separate. Distinguish. Decouple. Isolate. Differentiate.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;One thing’s rarely everything, unless you make it so.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;-Jason&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>Jason Fried</name>
      <email>jason@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/36878</id>
    <published>2024-05-03T20:04:00Z</published>
    <updated>2024-05-03T20:04:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/jason/why-am-i-still-doing-this-b931cdf8"/>
    <title>Why am I still doing this?</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;I’ve been doing this for 25 years, so I’ll often be asked why I’m still in it and how I stay motivated.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It ain’t the money, as I’ve been fortunate enough to make more than I’ll ever be able to spend.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I enjoy the work and we have a great crew, each a true pleasure to work with. I remain filled with ideas. So that’s part of it.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But it’s more that than. It’s more of a justice thing, really.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Look at this screenshot.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;  &lt;figure class="attachment attachment--preview attachment--lightboxable attachment--png"&gt;
      &lt;a download="IMG_4565.PNG" title="Download IMG_4565.PNG" data-click-proxy-target="lightbox_link_blob_1644165819" href="https://world.hey.com/jason/b931cdf8/blobs/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaHNLd2U3K3Y5aCIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoiYmxvYl9pZCJ9fQ==--7fa0b5582694f997b3b02922d49e063abde5c428/IMG_4565.PNG?disposition=attachment"&gt;
        &lt;img src="https://world.hey.com/jason/b931cdf8/representations/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaHNLd2U3K3Y5aCIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoiYmxvYl9pZCJ9fQ==--7fa0b5582694f997b3b02922d49e063abde5c428/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaDdDam9MWm05eWJXRjBTU0lJVUU1SEJqb0dSVlE2RkhKbGMybDZaVjkwYjE5c2FXMXBkRnNIYVFLQUIya0NBQVU2REhGMVlXeHBkSGxwU3pvTGJHOWhaR1Z5ZXdZNkNYQmhaMlV3T2cxamIyRnNaWE5qWlZRPSIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoidmFyaWF0aW9uIn19--954a41f9bb07721fde9715fc496c60558e15dcdb/IMG_4565.PNG" alt="IMG_4565.PNG" srcset="https://world.hey.com/jason/b931cdf8/representations/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaHNLd2U3K3Y5aCIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoiYmxvYl9pZCJ9fQ==--7fa0b5582694f997b3b02922d49e063abde5c428/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaDdDam9MWm05eWJXRjBTU0lJVUU1SEJqb0dSVlE2RkhKbGMybDZaVjkwYjE5c2FXMXBkRnNIYVFJQUQya0NBQW82REhGMVlXeHBkSGxwUVRvTGJHOWhaR1Z5ZXdZNkNYQmhaMlV3T2cxamIyRnNaWE5qWlZRPSIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoidmFyaWF0aW9uIn19--31b9702e5f0bc80fedf07f933f8dd65b979b93eb/IMG_4565.PNG 2x, https://world.hey.com/jason/b931cdf8/representations/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaHNLd2U3K3Y5aCIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoiYmxvYl9pZCJ9fQ==--7fa0b5582694f997b3b02922d49e063abde5c428/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaDdDam9MWm05eWJXRjBTU0lJVUU1SEJqb0dSVlE2RkhKbGMybDZaVjkwYjE5c2FXMXBkRnNIYVFLQUZta0NBQTg2REhGMVlXeHBkSGxwUERvTGJHOWhaR1Z5ZXdZNkNYQmhaMlV3T2cxamIyRnNaWE5qWlZRPSIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoidmFyaWF0aW9uIn19--815294f3017d0917c8380ce82bae1107fe19175e/IMG_4565.PNG 3x" decoding="async" loading="lazy"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;This is software my neighborhood uses to manage guest parking passes. It’s shit. Maybe you recognize it, maybe you don’t, but the name doesn’t matter.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;You know what the company charges for the privilege of using it? $10,000/year. $10,000 A YEAR! $10,000 year after year of our HOA budget goes to this crap. It feels borderline criminal.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I’m still doing this because the world is flooded with overpriced, crappy, subpar software. It hurts people and it hurts the economy.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I feel a moral obligation to do what I can to replace bad options with great options, at vastly reduced prices. I even want to replace great options with equally great options, just at reduced prices. Good software should not be expensive.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Software is an absolute miracle. You can make exceptionally good stuff at exceptionally reasonable prices. It’s not like hardware manufacturing where you have to cut all sorts of corners to keep costs in check, or charge a ton for stuff that’s truly well made. Raw materials, machinery, manufacturing, tight tolerances, physics — this stuff costs a lot to get right. Software does not.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Yet bad — and great software, frankly — remains way over priced.  And some is absolute highway robbery. Like this parking pass software. It’s clear no one cared about it — it’s just built to some spec by people who will never use it. It’s all there, the features tick the boxes, and technically it works, but we’d never ever find it acceptable if it was a physical product. But since it’s software, it can suck and we can still be sold on a $10,000/year contract.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;This fuels me.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;So hell yeah I’m motivated. And the more bad stuff I bump into, or even great stuff with silly numbers attached, the more motivated I get. It’s a deep well that keeps on providing.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;To that end, we’ve just started working on two more new products this year. We’re on a tear. We’re going to keep on putting quality stuff out there at reasonable prices. Not just to prove that it can be done, but because it must be done.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;-Jason&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>Jason Fried</name>
      <email>jason@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/36718</id>
    <published>2024-04-26T17:06:54Z</published>
    <updated>2024-04-26T17:06:54Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/jason/osmo-wiio-communication-usually-fails-except-by-accident-73a8ff2b"/>
    <title>Osmo Wiio: Communication usually fails, except by accident</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Osmo_Antero_Wiio"&gt;Osmo Wiio&lt;/a&gt; was a Finnish researcher of human communication. His laws of communication are the human communications equivalent of Murphy’s Laws.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Wiio's laws state...&lt;strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;If communication can fail, it will.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;If a message can be understood in different ways, it will be understood in just that way which does the most harm.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;There is always somebody who knows better than you what you meant by your message.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;The more communication there is, the more difficult it is for communication to succeed.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;And I particularly like his observation that anytime there are two people conversing, there are actually six people in the conversation:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;Who you think you are&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Who you think the other person is&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Who you think the other person thinks you are&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Who the other person thinks they are&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Who the other person thinks you are&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;Who the other person thinks you think they are.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;I'd say he's spot on across the board.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;-Jason&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>Jason Fried</name>
      <email>jason@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/36487</id>
    <published>2024-04-13T20:56:42Z</published>
    <updated>2024-04-13T20:56:42Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/jason/surface-area-vs-depth-in-product-design-eabd0cb4"/>
    <title>Surface area vs. Depth in product design</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;Some of the most rewarding features to add to products are ones that don’t increase surface area, but increase depth.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;This is how you continue to make a product a whole lot better without it feeling like it got a whole lot bigger.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Basecamp’s new References feature is a great example of this.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Video + write-up:&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href="https://updates.37signals.com/post/new-in-basecamp-references"&gt;https://updates.37signals.com/post/new-in-basecamp-references&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Barely any surface area — just a subtle tab down by the comments section. It’s almost not even there. Easy to ignore if you aren’t interested, but click that tab and a whole world of connections opens up. That’s the depth.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;All the sudden you can see how this is related to that, who’s referenced it across the entire system, how recently it’s been discussed (is it “alive” or “dead”), and where the energy is around the topic.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Surface area vs. Depth. An important thing to internalize when designing products.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;-Jason&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>Jason Fried</name>
      <email>jason@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/36311</id>
    <published>2024-04-04T16:08:20Z</published>
    <updated>2024-04-04T16:08:20Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/jason/motivation-50ab8280"/>
    <title>Motivation</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;I can fake enough. I can fake a lot.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But I’ve noticed there’s one thing in particular I can’t fake: Motivation.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;And in the end, at least for me, it all comes down to motivation. I may have the talent, I may know the tricks, I may be able to go through the motions.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But if I deeply don’t want to do it, it won’t be good. Simple as that. It might get done, or more likely it may not, but it’ll be hollow. Something will be missing.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;And that’s the spiral — doing empty work dissolves my motivation even more.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I’m more likely to do something I’m terrible at if I really want it, than something I’m great at that I don’t.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Motivation is my essential element. And you can’t mine it. It mines you.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;-Jason&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>Jason Fried</name>
      <email>jason@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/35901</id>
    <published>2024-03-14T16:31:06Z</published>
    <updated>2024-03-14T16:31:06Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/jason/avoiding-pile-ups-88f71f6b"/>
    <title>Avoiding pile-ups</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;One of the reasons we work in six week cycles, is that it gives us a different definition of later.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;When you work on really long projects — say 3, 6, 9 month projects — or projects that don’t have any end in sight, “we can do that later” typically means you’ll get to it eventually, as part of the current project. Long time frames give you invisible space to pack away unrealistic amounts of work. Since later is so far away, there’s no harm in kicking the can down the line. In other words, later makes a pile at the end.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Gnarly problem you can’t figure out how to solve yet? Punt it into the later pile. Design not coming together quite right? Toss it in the later pile. Taking on lots of technical debt as you go? Push it into the later pile.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But then as you near the end, you run into this big pile of stuff you said you’d eventually deal with, fix, redesign, tighten up, etc. But there rarely seems to be enough time at the end, so you either end up guiltily ignoring it entirely, or hastily patching it together with duct tape. And when you hastily patch, you often end up creating another fix-it-up project later.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But, when you work in six week cycles, or relatively short time frames, later means something else entirely. There’s no time for later. It’s now or not. Later doesn’t mean we’ll get to it at the end of this cycle. It means we’ll drop it. Later means another time, not this time. Later isn’t an obligation, it’s a maybe. Later isn’t a cage, it’s freedom. It’s not a debt to pay off, it’s an asset. There’s no pile of pile ups, there’s no guilt, there’s no feeling of late nights and crunch time ahead. Later simply means not now, not soon, and not for sure.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;That’s the kind of later we like.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;-Jason&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>Jason Fried</name>
      <email>jason@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/35635</id>
    <published>2024-03-03T22:14:08Z</published>
    <updated>2024-03-03T22:14:08Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/jason/hooks-towel-bars-and-software-14c66c8c"/>
    <title>Hooks, towel bars, and software</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;Strangely, a recent bathroom renovation crystalized my perspective on product development.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;When being asked to choose between towel hooks or a towel bar, the choice was obvious: Hooks, of course.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Hooks take up no space. Towel bars suck up space.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Hooks hold towels no matter how you place them. Towel bars require towels to be balanced lest they slide off.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Towels naturally look good and drape well on hooks. Towels on bars require effort to display well.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Hooks can hold anything with a loop or a bend or a catch — loofas, shower caps, hats, rain soaked jackets and backpacks, etc. Towel bars can’t hold nearly as much, even though they take up much more space.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Hooks can hold multiple towels at once, with enough air getting to multiple layers because of the uneven ridges that single point hanging creates. Towel bars layer wet towels, leaving ones at the bottom or middle struggling to dry.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;You can’t mount a hook crookedly. You can absolutely mount a towel bar unevenly.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Reasons go on.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But what do towel hooks have to do with product development? For me, just about everything. They’re a frame, they’re a lens, they’re aspirational. A hook holds more than towels — it holds lessons in how to build.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;We aim to make hooks. I want our products full of hooks. Simple, flexible, you-can’t-do-it-wrong hooks. Hooks that just work, no fuss.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;When working on new products, new features, and improving existing stuff, I’m visualizing the “hook-ness” of what we're building. Making small, flexible features with minimal surface area that can be used intuitively in obvious ways without the possibility of doing it wrong. That’s the magic formula, that’s our model.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The unassuming, humble hook is a high bar.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;-Jason&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>Jason Fried</name>
      <email>jason@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/35518</id>
    <published>2024-02-27T17:20:20Z</published>
    <updated>2024-02-27T17:20:20Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/jason/do-learn-54ece4d4"/>
    <title>Do learn</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;Imagine teaching guitar without putting an instrument in someone’s hands.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Or teaching ceramics without having people work with clay.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Or teaching tennis without swinging the racket and hitting balls.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I’m sure there’s &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; way to teach those things without doing those things, but come on, we all know you have to do those things to &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; learn those things.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I believe business is in the same category. It’s much closer to learning an art, sport, or instrument than it is to learning history, political science, or another subject primarily taught through written texts, lectures, or observing without doing.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Yet how many entrepreneurship programs out there require their students to start a real business? They may exist, but I’ve been around and haven’t seen one yet. It can be the simplest damn business — buying and selling on eBay, for example — but it’s got to be a business with costs, products or services, and sales to customers. And it should start on day one, class one, and go at least as long as the course allows. The businesses that are started, and the struggles and successes that ensue, should be the subject matter, period.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Instead, there’s a lot of talk. There’s a lot of abstraction. There’s a lot of strategizing. There’s a lot of business plan writing. There’s a lot of game play. There’s a lot of theorizing. And there are plenty of case studies.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But there’s very little guitar being played, clay being formed, and balls being hit.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Imagine learning guitar by planning how you’re going to play. Or learning how to throw a pot on a wheel by presenting a Powerpoint on it. Or learning how to keep the ball in the lines by studying how the lines were painted.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;We’d roll our eyes. And rightfully so.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Yet this is how entrepreneurship is taught.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Heads should roll. And rightfully so.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Give me two people — Person A has spent two years in business school studying how to start a business that doesn’t yet exist. Person B has never set foot in business school, but has been running their own business for two years.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Who’s learned more about entrepreneurship along the way? Who has the advantage in year three?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I know who I’m picking. You?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;To learn business, do business.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;-Jason&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>Jason Fried</name>
      <email>jason@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/35395</id>
    <published>2024-02-21T22:05:21Z</published>
    <updated>2024-02-21T23:30:46Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/jason/you-couldn-t-know-3d98330d"/>
    <title>You couldn't know</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;Have you ever been asked &amp;quot;What do you wish you knew then that you know now?&amp;quot;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;I have. And I hate the question.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;It's usually framed in a way that encourages you to pretend to place yourself in the nascent days of your career, or early adulthood. Back when you didn't know much, when you were trying to figure things out.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Essentially it's asking you which mistakes you wish you didn't make. To squint and identify the things you could have bypassed if you were armed with the wisdom of hindsight.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;My take? I think you’d have made the same mistakes, and I don’t think you could have avoided anything that happened.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Why? First, it assumes you'd even listen to your 50 year old self when you were 20. Next it assumes you'd even be ready and able to accept the advice you didn't recognize as relevant. Last it assumes you'd be able to avoid the things you didn't see coming.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;I don't think you could, would, or should.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Learning is experiencing and doing. It’s not dodging, following, or forgoing.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;You had to go through the shit to learn the shit. Sidestepping it would have just landed you in some other shit. And then you'd have wished you had listened to different advice.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;You wouldn’t have your sage advice today if you hadn’t had the stupid experiences then! In fact, answering the question would erase present you from existence. Because if you were different then, you wouldn’t be the you you know now.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Are there mistakes I wish I hadn’t made? One one hand, absolutely — plenty — but on the other hand, I had to make them to be who I am now. There’s no version of me that’s present me today with a different set of events in the past. I like who I am now, even with portions of my past I’m less satisfied with peering through present day goggles.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;But it’s a fantasy to think that if I’d just had magical advice from some old dude named me, then I wouldn’t have made those mistakes back then.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Cut yourself some slack.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;-Jason&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>Jason Fried</name>
      <email>jason@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/35369</id>
    <published>2024-02-20T20:02:12Z</published>
    <updated>2024-02-20T20:02:12Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/jason/don-t-delegate-your-word-1875de99"/>
    <title>Don't delegate your word</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;As you build your business, you'll end up delegating plenty.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Much of what you did before is now better done by someone else.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;To make more progress, you release your grip and allow.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But there’s one thing you should hold tight and never let go. It’s the thing that should never be delegated.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It’s your voice.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Speak for yourself. Don’t let anyone speak for you. Don’t have someone else Tweet on your behalf. Or write posts under your name. Or take your calls. Or read or respond to your emails.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;No assistant. No replacement. No simulation.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;How can you take someone at their word when it's not their word?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The moment it’s not you to someone on the other end, you’ve lost something you’ll never get back. If they write you, and they don’t get you back, you’ve gone wrong.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Yes it’s more work. But it’s your work, and your obligation. You = you is the equation to solve.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Don’t outgrow that.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;-Jason&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>Jason Fried</name>
      <email>jason@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/35042</id>
    <published>2024-02-07T21:00:33Z</published>
    <updated>2024-02-07T22:00:26Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/jason/the-data-came-from-where-a82d198d"/>
    <title>The data came from where?</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;Now you have the data.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Thousands of responses from a survey with dozens of questions.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;You worked hard to come up with questions that painted the picture you felt you needed to make the decision with the data you gathered.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;And now you've got it. Comprehensively. Quantitatively. You're data driven, and now you have the stuff that drives you.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;You're more sure than ever.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But wait a second. Where did that data come from?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Your survey, yeah... But where did the questions come from?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Best practices? Opinions on what to ask and how to ask it? According to who? Are you sure those words before the question marks were the right ones? What if the questions were asked differently?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;So much certainty coming out, so little going in.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&amp;quot;How often do you...&amp;quot; vs &amp;quot;How often would you...&amp;quot; vs. &amp;quot;Last week did you?&amp;quot;. The responses to those could be wildly different. Did you check your words as closely as you checked your results?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;If you slide back a few steps, you'll see that it's all a judgement call. How you asked, what you asked, when you asked, which words you paired together, how you started the question... All these things matter. In fact, they are the matter that form the answer.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;And you know what? There's no right way. Which is the exactly the point I'm trying to make.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Your hard data comes from subjectivity. A sense of solidity built from mush. False confidence at the finish line, from a shapeshifting starting line.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's all a judgement call. Even the stuff you can measure.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;And it's a beautiful thing.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;-Jason&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>Jason Fried</name>
      <email>jason@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/34981</id>
    <published>2024-02-05T21:29:15Z</published>
    <updated>2024-02-05T21:29:15Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/jason/making-it-balance-5056a8fb"/>
    <title>Making it balance</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;One of my greatest pleasures at work is trying to find that point where everything feels just right. Nothing more, nothing less, but right there in the pocket.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;It's almost fractal. It's there in every component, in every feature, in every flow, in every sequence, in every product, in every decision, inside everything across the company.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;How do you know when it's just right? It's the same feeling you get when you try to balance something physical.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;You know it. You put something on something else and try to find that center of gravity... A bit to the right, oops too much. Lean back to the left... Steady... Steady... Ugh, too much push. Stack it up again, find that center... Wobble, bobble, almost... And then it locks in. Da! There it is.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;All the sudden the pushing and pulling forces disappear and it's just there, on its own. Still, in harmony and equanimity. That's what just right feels like.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;It's easy to experience physically because our bodies speak the language. We feel the weight, we intuit the momentum. Our internal gyroscopes sense  balance, and transfers it into objects we touch.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;But when it comes to intellectual, conceptual things like business or software, we have to shift into the imagined sense of balance. We don't get the free borders, edges, weights, shapes, and gravity, to help us find that middle. Muscles don't pull on tendons don't pull on bones. Our nerves don't get the signals for free.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;So I imagine. If this was physical, would it balance? I literally think about the center of gravity of an idea, a feature, a button, an idea, a product. Is there too much weight over here? Too much over there? If this whole thing was in stone, would it crash to one side? Or would it stand a chance of staying upright? Would it be at rest, or would it want to fall?&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Once you find that spot — the right set of features, the right flows, the right yesses and the right no's, you stop. That's v1. Once you find the balance, you aim to stay in balance. Adding more, but in a balanced way to maintain the form, to keep the center. To hold steady.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;It's a beautiful thing.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;That's how I think about making products.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;-Jason&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>Jason Fried</name>
      <email>jason@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/34977</id>
    <published>2024-02-05T17:52:23Z</published>
    <updated>2024-02-05T18:08:56Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/jason/basecamp-turns-20-a34c88e1"/>
    <title>Basecamp turns 20</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;20 years ago today &lt;a href="https://signalvnoise.com/archives/000542"&gt;I wrote a blog post&lt;/a&gt; that changed my life.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I'd never really launched a product before, so posting to our blog was only way I knew how to do it. And social media hadn't even been invented yet, so where else was I supposed to put it? In fact, guess what else happened to launch the same day as Basecamp? Facebook. So we're talking the stone age.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I was announcing this new thing we built called &lt;a href="https://basecamp.com"&gt;Basecamp&lt;/a&gt;. It was a project management tool that we made for ourselves. At the time we were a web design firm, and we just didn't have a good way to collaborate with each other and keep our clients in the loop. We didn't have a place to make announcements, keep feedback on the record, and generally keep things centralized in a way that would keep everyone accountable.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;We figured if we needed it, plenty of others probably did too.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;And it turns out they did! We were right.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Not only was Basecamp something entirely new at the time, the distribution model, and business model, were new too. We weren't the first to offer software as a subscription service, but we were very, very early. So early in fact that the bank wouldn't allow us to accept annual payments on credit cards because they didn't want to be on the hook if this new software as a subscription service model thing didn't work out in a few months. That's why we could only initially bill monthly! Which turned out to be a pretty good thing in the end.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;You never know what's going to happen until after it happens.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;And happen it did. We had this idea that, I don't know, if we could maybe make $5,000 a month after the first year, we'd be on to something. That would be a nice $60,000/year business, which we'd feather into our web design business. We'd essentially treat it as a perpetual client — we being our own client.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Turns out that we hit that $5000/month mark in a few weeks. And a year or so later, Basecamp was generating more revenue for us than our web design business. So we shut that part of the business down and went all-in on Basecamp. And software in general.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;So much came from Basecamp. And so much still does. Rails came from Basecamp. And tens of thousands of programming careers came from Rails. Other businesses sprang up. Software as a service was further legitimized. And the cycle that began back in the early 2000s continues to spin strongly today.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's been the professional honor of a lifetime to be able to build something that matters to so many, and to build that thing alongside so many extraordinary people, for so many extraordinary people. From co-workers to customers to fellow business owners, and everyone I've met along the way, what an incredible ride it's been so far. And today's Basecamp is the best it's ever been, by far. It's a thrill to watch whole new generation of entrepreneurs, product teams, and small businesses are discovering the secret so many have known: &lt;a href="https://basecamp.com/customers"&gt;Businesses simply run better on Basecamp&lt;/a&gt;. There really is something radically different about it. In this business, longevity isn't a fluke.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;As 2024 marks 20 years of Basecamp, it also marks 25 years of &lt;a href="https://37signals.com"&gt;37signals&lt;/a&gt;. 2024 also marks the beginning of something brand new from us called &lt;a href="https://once.com"&gt;ONCE&lt;/a&gt;. It's our year of new. It'll be interesting to see if we're early again.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;When you've been around an industry long enough, you get to see how cyclical everything is. The Earth is round, and so are trends. When you're close to something, it looks like it's on a straight line forever, but when you step back, and wait awhile, you'll often see it crest the curve, bend out of view, and eventually sneak back up on you from behind. Oh, that again! I remember that. Yeah, that was good. One of the real treats of a long career is to revisit the past and pull some of those better ideas ahead into the present.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Right now it feels like we've got a bag of bright ideas slung over our shoulder. And we're headed out for new horizons.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I feel so fortunate, and so grateful. Thank you.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;-Jason&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>Jason Fried</name>
      <email>jason@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/34858</id>
    <published>2024-01-31T21:54:27Z</published>
    <updated>2024-01-31T21:54:27Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/jason/enough-feedback-ccbc303c"/>
    <title>Enough feedback</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;Enough feedback comes quick.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Invite 100, get 10, 5 probably tell you all you need to know. Or at least 80% of it, which is all you need to know.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Another 10, 20, 50+ will end up telling you mostly the same as those core five. And you'll find yourself repeating yourself — explaining the same thing you already explained, just to new people. Or thanking them for reports you've already received. The stuff that you loved learning the first time becomes irritating after three more people tell you three more times.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It doesn't matter if there's a place to see everything that's already been reported — no one's looking at that before they report what's already been reported. It's just human nature. They're just trying to be helpful, they aren't here to check their work.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Of course more opinions and perspectives shine new lights through different lenses, but the beams converge on the initial spot provided by that original group of five.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Never fault those who share because you asked. You're lucky they care enough to give. But remember that feedback comes fast, and too much of a good thing can create a mess to manage. That's on you, not them.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;-Jason&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>Jason Fried</name>
      <email>jason@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/34446</id>
    <published>2024-01-17T05:02:29Z</published>
    <updated>2024-01-17T05:05:34Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/jason/it-s-all-a-judgment-call-6ab5d025"/>
    <title>It’s all a judgment call</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;It's all a judgment call. Every human decision is a gut decision. The decision itself is the messy integration of many disparate pieces of information, experiences, instincts, stories, and unknowns.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Data may inform, but as long as a human is making the decision, it's ultimately a judgment call. If you're just going by the data, then you're confirming, not deciding. Machines are better at that than you'll ever be.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;A decision is a point of view seen through a million lenses, many of which are invisible even to the one deciding. The lenses are formed by every experience that person has ever had, their imagination, and, in many ways, the generations of people that came before them in order for them to be here. An experience doesn't exist without a prior experience. And every past colors every future.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Think about it. When companies hire executives, they ultimately hire on experience and judgment. Hiring itself is a judgment call about other people's future judgement calls.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Narrow it down to three extraordinary candidates. What sets them apart? It's the stuff gleaned through conversation, not questionnaires or test results. That's why we interview, and don't choose our best algorithmically. Competency is bigger than &amp;quot;can they do it&amp;quot;. Competency is &amp;quot;how they do it.&amp;quot; Can is clean and binary, how is messy and analog.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In many ways, the output of any company is that company's collective judgment about what to do, how to do it, why to do it, and when to do it. Each one of these is a loose collection of prior judgment calls made by individuals, all unique in their own experiences.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Give 10 companies the same data, the same facts, and the same amount of time, and you're going to still have 10 different outcomes. Because all those clean binaries are transmuted through the messy analog that is judgment.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;At least that's what I think.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;-Jason&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>Jason Fried</name>
      <email>jason@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/34435</id>
    <published>2024-01-16T23:09:31Z</published>
    <updated>2024-01-16T23:16:25Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/jason/apple-vision-pro-pov-d6ffafaf"/>
    <title>Apple Vision Pro POV</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;The thing that excites me most about the &lt;a href="https://www.apple.com/apple-vision-pro/"&gt;Apple Vision Pro&lt;/a&gt; is the ability to capture someone's point of view.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;General purpose vision tracking at this scale and resolution, in a consumer device, is entirely new thing. And I think it has the potential to alter the course of the human experience.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Cameras can record a scene. Video cameras can record many scenes at a high frame rate. And a skilled photographer or cinematographer / director duo can direct your gaze at a specific point, region, or sequence. And that's resulted in amazing pictures, movies, and visual experiences.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But what I think is super interesting about the Apple Vision Pro is the potential to be able to literally see through someone else's eyes. Not just see their field of vision — you can get at that with head or eyeglass mounted cameras — but to actually see where they're looking. To know what they're focused on. To lock in with them. To see how they see. To watch them look from their point of view.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Standing in someone's shoes is one thing, but even if you could do that, you'd still be looking through your own eyes. But to literally see as they'd see from someone else's point-of-view perspective feels groundbreaking.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;If I was making an app for this, I'd call it &amp;quot;See With&amp;quot;.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Imagine being able to see with an artist. What do they look at when they paint? Where are they looking? How are they looking? How often are they darting around, vs. fixing their focus on a specific spot? When they choose a brush, are they looking at the toe, the belly, or the heel of the brush? Or is the right handle they're after for the control they seek?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Imagine being able to &lt;em&gt;see with&lt;/em&gt; a furniture designer. What do they look at specifically when they look at a piece of wood? How do they see the grain? When do they look at the whole vs. the tiniest detail. How do they see their tools. How do their eyes help them make their choices and decisions?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Imagine being able to &lt;em&gt;see with&lt;/em&gt; a florist. What part of the flower are they looking at? What catches them? When they look at entire bouquet, what bits do they focus on first? When they're looking through 36 roses, how do they see those? What are they looking at to pick that specific one?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Imagine being able to &lt;em&gt;see with&lt;/em&gt; a programmer. When they look at code, what do they see? Where are they looking? What are they looking for? How often are they referencing this bit or that bit? Do they continually read through the entire thing like a story, or are they just focused on one line at a time? How do they spot a bug?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Same with a writer. A drummer. A driver. A fly fisherman. A landscape designer. A tailor. The list goes on.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I'd find this endlessly fascinating. Add in voiceover where someone can describe what's going through their head while they work, choose, consider, and see, and you've got a first-person observational learning experience that's radically new.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I hope this happens.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>Jason Fried</name>
      <email>jason@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/34307</id>
    <published>2024-01-12T18:09:43Z</published>
    <updated>2024-01-12T18:10:04Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/jason/swimming-the-center-or-the-edge-a61c6187"/>
    <title>Swimming the center or the edge</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;Imagine a vast swimming pool 25 miles long, 50 miles wide, and 25 feet deep. Swimming this pool is akin to running a business. And how you swim this pool is akin to how you run the business.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Everyone starts at the beginning, but you decide how close to the center or the edge you swim. There’s only one rule: You can’t turn around, there’s no going back.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Where would you start?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Given the dimensions of the pool, here’s how I’d do it: I’d start near the edge. The edge effectively creates multiple “shores”. You can swim all the way to the end, or you can grab the side and stop for a breath, a break, or even decide “that’s enough” and stop there. This is optionality. More points of survival. To me this represents independence.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But not everyone decides to start at the edge. Oftentimes, a key strategic decision pushes them center: Raising money. And the more money they raise, the further center they’re pushed. At some point, there’s only one way to make the business work: To reach the other side. Once you begin, the edges are further away than the end. There’s no optionality, you can’t stop. You either make it across, or you die.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The choice between VC funding and bootstrapping independently depends on an entrepreneur's appetite for risk and personal definition of success. VC funding is typically for those who aim for a singular, large-scale “win”, while bootstrapping appeals to those seeking path with multiple potential outcomes along the way. One wants it all, while the other wants enough.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Realistically, there are other places to start than just the edge or the center. You can start further center but still closer to the edge. But the further center you go, the more risk you take, and the fewer options you have. Every entrepreneur has to figure out what makes sense for them, but for me, optionality is worth more than one big outcome.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;What about you?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;-Jason&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>Jason Fried</name>
      <email>jason@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/34031</id>
    <published>2024-01-03T23:53:19Z</published>
    <updated>2024-01-04T00:16:17Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/jason/to-make-5a88817f"/>
    <title>To make</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;I've consulted. I've done client work. I've advised. I've served on boards. I've invested. I've written books. I've spoken on the circuit. I've blogged for years.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I have to say, I've found no greater professional joy than working with a tight group of people to ship and support &lt;strong&gt;our own products&lt;/strong&gt;. And for those products to find people willing to trade their own hard earned treasure for a little bit of ours.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Betting on an idea — and seeing it through — is enormously fulfilling. The creative and intellectual stimulation is beyond compare. Especially when you're the first customer for anything you make.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;When I was a consultant doing work for hire I thought it was the peak. I got to bounce from client to client, sign big contracts, do a lot of work, cash large checks, etc. But then you realize most of what you do is never implemented. Yes, you got paid for it, but it was just advice, recommendations, and suggestions. Words on pages that were received, but not really read. Designs in files that were delivered, but never really deployed. There was nothing there in the end. You didn't get to make any bets, you just played with someone else's chips.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;You thought you were changing things. Changing them. But it wasn't change, it was an exchange. You handed it over, they handed you something in return, and that was that.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I'm glad I went through it, otherwise I wouldn't have known it.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Been giving other people advice for years? Give yourself the advice and see if it's any good. Meet the market.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Go make something. Join a team that's making something. Put your fingerprint on something that won't just sit on the shelf somewhere.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;-Jason&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>Jason Fried</name>
      <email>jason@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/33816</id>
    <published>2023-12-27T00:46:16Z</published>
    <updated>2023-12-27T01:07:11Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/jason/cars-and-business-eea60b8d"/>
    <title>Cars and business</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;I’m going to draw a parallel that isn’t quite straight, but it’s close enough.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It’s between old (analog) cars and new (digital) cars, simple (analog) businesses and complicated (digital) businesses.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Lately I’ve been driving two distinctly different cars. One from 1970, and the other from 2023. They essentially have nothing in common other than that you sit in them, they have four tires that contact the road, and you control them with a steering wheel and pedals.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Some who don’t care much for cars might say that’s everything in common. On paper I can see the argument, but get behind the wheel of both, and go for a drive, and you wouldn’t say the experiences were equivalent. They’re as different as different can be.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The 1970s experience is analog. Your leg strength determines your stopping power. The road surface below clearly communicates with your ass. The steering wheel actually feels like it’s turning the wheels. The windows roll down by turning a crank that literally rolls them down. Switches snick, dials click. This is a direct experience, with mechanical feedback, requiring full attention and real effort.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;The 2023 experience is digital. Nearly everything is abstracted. The brakes are heavily mechanically assisted. Steering even more so. You can’t really feel the road surface because the suspension masterfully absorbs every little detail. Even the buttons have been replaced by touchscreens with haptics. This is an indirect experience, with simulated feedback, requiring some attention and little effort.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Which you prefer is up to you. I happen to love both for different reasons.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;And that’s just driving. The gulf is wider when it comes to repair.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;With an old analog car, a problem’s cause is more obvious. Linkages are visible, this connects to that, teeth mesh to move gears which move shafts which move wheels. When something’s broken it’s generally confirmable with a common tool and a set of eyeballs. Any mechanic with a basic understanding can diagnose any problem relatively easily — sometime solely by ear. There are only so many things it could be, and they’re all right in front of you.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;With a modern new car, computers enter the picture. Engines are covered, sometimes even inaccessible. Cars crash, but so does firmware. This doesn’t turn that, this sends electrons to that, which are then interpreted by circuits and software and systems.  Which one’s to blame when something doesn’t work? It’ll take a while to find out, and at least $1000. Almost anything can be wrong, and you’ll have to leave the car at the shop for a while so they can plug it in and run diagnostics. The human defers to the machine to tell us.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Pros and cons for sure.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Now for the parallels to business.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Through this car experience lens, I’ve come to see businesses as either analog or digital too. I’m not describing their product or what they make. I’m talking about how they’re structured, how they run. An analog business can make software, and a digital business can make pizza.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;An analog business is direct. It’s clear what does what, and how it does it. When something changes, you typically know what changed. There’s some suspension to absorb the bumps, but it’s basic — you’re never too far removed from the root cause. There are fewer managers and more doers. There’s less distance between the customer and the maker. Feedback is heard, not interpreted and translated. No decks, just conversations and writing.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;A digital business is indirect and abstracted. The structure is obscured, riddled with departments and groups run by other groups. Decisions are complicated because one too many people are involved. What should be simple has become complex — the result of process that serves the prospect, not the purpose. Everything is padded. Getting to someone requires going through something. Customers are a concept, sliced by demographics. Everything’s a presentation rather than a conversation.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;As usual, the analogies and metaphors don’t map perfectly, but hopefully you feel what I’m getting at. Does it resonate?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I aim to run an analog business. Direct, clear, obvious, fair, and easy to fix.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;-Jason&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>Jason Fried</name>
      <email>jason@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/33002</id>
    <published>2023-11-27T21:46:11Z</published>
    <updated>2023-11-27T21:46:11Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/jason/live-with-it-for-a-while-a9191f5f"/>
    <title>Live with it for a while</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;In the course of building products, you'll likely experience moments when you're unsure of a certain screen, flow, condition, label, idea, whatever.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Maybe this button doesn't feel right. Or the name of this feature feels unresolved. Or some color is jarring, but kind of interesting nonetheless. Or the way something gets set up seems a bit kludgy at the moment. Maybe this stuff is alright, maybe it's not, but it feels unsettled.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;I like these moments. It's practice. It's a chance to sit with them, to let them be, to work on other things while they marinate in the back of your mind. They aren't blockers, they aren't deal breakers — they're just things that may or may not work out.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Sometimes time makes them work. Or reveals that they certainly don't. Sometimes they weren't that important anyway, and it's just a matter of getting used to them. Sometimes they're novel and unusual — which can be jarring to the uninitiated — but endearing to the experienced. Sometimes!&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;So just let them be. Come back around to them later if they continue to bug you. It's perfectly OK to leave things unresolved, and let the resolution force itself on you eventually. If you forget about them, they didn't matter anyway. If you can't forget, maybe they do matter more than you realized.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Projects unfold. Live with them for a while. The answers will reveal themselves when they're ready.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;-Jason&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>Jason Fried</name>
      <email>jason@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/32706</id>
    <published>2023-11-16T17:37:55Z</published>
    <updated>2023-11-16T17:37:55Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/jason/commodities-generics-and-software-393ccf10"/>
    <title>Commodities, generics, and software</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;Once a product category proves popular, it's common for more companies to enter the market. Eventually, many options appear that are essentially mostly the same. Now we've got something that quacks like a commodity.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Once we've got a commodity, generics eventually follow. Devoid of fancy packaging, marketing, and advertising, prices fall while quality remains perfectly acceptable.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Brand name products might be slightly better on some dimensions, but it ultimately becomes a value judgement. A few bucks difference? The confidence of buying a brand name still feels worth it. Many, many bucks different? Maybe not.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;This happens in most industries. Maybe not in airplanes, but absolutely in peanut butter. And you know what's closer to peanut butter than airplanes? Software is.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Strangely, many software categories have commoditized, but, given that nearly everything is a service these days, operational costs have remained universally high. This makes it hard for lower priced generics to creep in. This means people continue to pay luxury prices for software services that are essentially commodities. We think something's wrong with that. Sounds like an opportunity.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;This is where ONCE comes in.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;One facet of our initial strategy with ONCE is to find those commoditized pay-forever services everyone's running, and make our own radically simplified &amp;quot;80/20&amp;quot; versions as pay-once products. And this time you get to own for less, not rent for more. And you'll get the code, too.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;In about a month we'll unveil the first ONCE product. Any guesses?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;-Jason&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>Jason Fried</name>
      <email>jason@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/32464</id>
    <published>2023-11-08T18:48:50Z</published>
    <updated>2023-11-08T18:48:50Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/jason/heard-something-read-something-saw-something-16-afce97da"/>
    <title>Heard Something, Read Something, Saw Something [#16]</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;Hey there!&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Here’s the 16th installment of my popular Heard Something, Read Something, Saw Something series.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;So, what do we have this time...&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Heard Something&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;Lately I've been enjoying listening to discussions about free will. Do we have it? If so, how much? Always? Sometimes? Never? Is it real or an illusion? I find the concept fascinating. One of my favorite recent conversations (debates?) about the topic was between Russ Roberts and Robert Sapolsky on Robert's EconTalk podcast. Listen in. &lt;br&gt;Hear it: &lt;a href="https://www.econtalk.org/robert-sapolsky-on-determinism-free-will-and-responsibility/"&gt;https://www.econtalk.org/robert-sapolsky-on-determinism-free-will-and-responsibility/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Read Something&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Every once in a while you read something that swirls with someone’s body of work and undeniably signals they definitively know what the fuck they’re doing. This is that, by Jonathan Hoefler.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Read it: &lt;a href="https://typography.com/blog/text-for-proofing-fonts"&gt;https://typography.com/blog/text-for-proofing-fonts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Saw Something&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;Driving Dreams is a wonderful documentary on the golden age of Italian automotive design. Full of colorful characters, poetic stories, and the celebration of an art form — and approach — that's now long gone. Well worth the 52 minutes.&lt;br&gt;See it: &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Driving-Dreams-Gianluca-Migliarotti/dp/B07455DCH7/"&gt;https://www.amazon.com/Driving-Dreams-Gianluca-Migliarotti/dp/B07455DCH7/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Until next time.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;BTW, if you like these, and think someone else might too, please forward it on. They can subscribe to my newsletter right at the top at &lt;a href="https://world.hey.com/jason"&gt;https://world.hey.com/jason&lt;/a&gt;. Thank you.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;-Jason&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>Jason Fried</name>
      <email>jason@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/32289</id>
    <published>2023-11-03T00:12:53Z</published>
    <updated>2023-11-03T21:43:30Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/jason/look-back-less-848e9db0"/>
    <title>Look back less</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;I have a theory.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;One of the reasons companies have a hard time moving forward is because they've tangled themselves in the near past. Eyes aimed backwards rather than ahead, staring at the dark, feet in their own concrete.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;They've trapped themselves looking for certainty where there isn't any. Searching for actionable advice where there are only guesses.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Something sorta went wrong. A project didn't go as planned. Some launch didn't meet expectations. A number someone felt was in reach didn't get hit.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;So they look back, scanning the ruins for something shiny. They gather people up and call for a search party. They launch into post-mortems and retrospectives.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's a mistake most of the time. And a waste of time almost all of the time.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Let's start with when it makes sense. If the process is highly mechanized, isolated, or systematized, then you can look back and find the exact moment when something went wrong. And you don't need to conjure up a &amp;quot;what if&amp;quot; counterfactual, you know for sure this was the point of failure.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;For example, if you're making widgets, and your small circular disks are coming out as half moons instead, then you can trace the process back, figure out where the stamping went wrong, correct that machine or process, and absolutely 100% fix the issue. If you can do that, by all means do that. Technical downtime can often be perfectly traced like that, too.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But so many failed projects subject to retrospectives are searching for reasons where there are only humans to be found.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Ever been on one that lasts hours only to determine &amp;quot;next time we need to communicate better&amp;quot;? I bet you have.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Or one that says &amp;quot;If we only would have involved QA earlier we would have caught that.&amp;quot; Or &amp;quot;Next time we need to be more careful to take seasonal timing into account&amp;quot;. Or &amp;quot;designers and programmers need to work more closely together.&amp;quot; Or some other generalized platitude, extruded from the retrospective process.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;There may be truth in the statements, but are they really the reason things didn't go as planned? Really? You sure? And those aren't actually answers, they remain questions without question marks. So now what, specifically? Spending hours of people's time grabbing for something grippy in the box of generalized excuses isn't going to turn up a treasure.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;And most of the time, reasons are actually mysteries. Or deeper than you can dig. Or too many to count. The world, the work, the market, the customer, the timing, the pressure, the economy at large, the expectations, the hopes and dreams are fuzzy, abstract, and irrational. You can point, but not at a point that's clearly defined enough to make a difference next time.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Counterfactuals are deeply satisfying because they can never be proven. They never have to smash into reality. Imagination takes hold, a scapegoat comes into focus, and we can blame it all on the thing we'll never know mattered in the first place. Report written, meeting adjourned!&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;A better path is to reflect forward, not backwards. Develop a loose theory while working on what's next. Appreciate there's no certainty to be found, and put all your energy into doing better on an upcoming project. But how will you do better next time if you don't know what went wrong last time? Nothing is guaranteed other than experience. You'll simply have more time under the curve, and more moments under tension, to perform better moving forward. Internalize as you go, not as you went.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;If you're any good, you'll simply do better next time because you're better at what you do than you were the last time you did it. That may be murky and unsatisfying for some, but I believe it to be absolutely true.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;So next time the involuntary instinct kicks in, and the urge to schedule a retro when something didn't go as planned, skip it and skip ahead. There's more to learn looking forward.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;-Jason&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>Jason Fried</name>
      <email>jason@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
</feed>
