<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xml:lang="en-US" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:/dhh/feed</id>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/dhh"/>
  <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/feed.atom"/>
  <title>David Heinemeier Hansson</title>
  <updated>2024-07-12T09:48:52Z</updated>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/38361</id>
    <published>2024-07-12T09:48:52Z</published>
    <updated>2024-07-12T09:48:52Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/living-with-linux-and-android-after-two-decades-of-apple-4f730084"/>
    <title>Living with Linux and Android after two decades of Apple</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;It now seems laughable that only a few months ago, I was questioning whether I'd actually be able to switch off the Apple stack and stick to my choice. That's what two decades worth of entrenched habits will do to your belief in change! But not only was it possible, it's been immensely enjoyable. What seemed so difficult at first now appears trivial, since it's been done.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;That's not a critique of the Apple ecosystem per se. Apple continues to make great hardware and pretty good software too. And I think accepting that fact from the get go actually makes sticking to a switch more likely to succeed. Falling in love with something new is a better and healthier motivator than hating something old.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;That's been my experience with Linux in particular. I've come to love the setup I've enshrined in the &lt;a href="https://omakub.org/"&gt;Omakub&lt;/a&gt; project. It does a whole host of things much nicer than the old macOS walled garden experience, on top of the fact that running an open source operating system simply feels right for someone who owes their entire career to open source. It's a positive vision: I really, &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; like what Linux has to offer these days.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;It's a similar feeling, albeit not as strong, with the switch to Android. I don't have any illusions that Google is any gentler of a corporate giant than Apple. The two have very similar ideas about extracting monopoly rents from their respective app stores. But the slogan that Android is more open is actually true.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;Now plenty of people don't really care about that openness, and that's fine. But I do. I care about being able to &lt;a href="https://www.fortnite.com/mobile/android"&gt;download the Fortnite APK straight from Epic Games&lt;/a&gt;, and being able to play our favorite family game with the kids, without having to ask someone for permission. Sure, it could be a bit more convenient if the game was available in the Play Store, but spending another two minutes doing the direct install is nothing against the hundreds of hours we've spent playing since.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;The same is true in terms of customization. I'm running this beautiful, minimal launcher called &lt;a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=app.olauncher&amp;amp;hl=en"&gt;olauncher&lt;/a&gt;, which turns Android into a far less addictive mobile experience by replacing icons and app drawers with a simple set of text links. It's great. And it's the kind of stuff you can only really do properly on Android, because replacing the default launcher is possible.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;Getting out of the Apple rut has also lead me to discover an amazing new world of both software and hardware. Solutions that I just wasn't in the market for after settling into an Apple grove over the years. Since switching to Linux, I've picked up &lt;a href="https://neovim.io/"&gt;Neovim&lt;/a&gt; as my new editor of choice, I've fallen in love with the &lt;a href="https://frame.work/products/laptop13-diy-intel-ultra-1"&gt;Framework 13&lt;/a&gt; laptop, and recently, I've even gotten into mechanical keyboards (the current choice being the &lt;a href="https://nuphy.com/products/air75-v2"&gt;NuPhy Air75&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;That's what a change of scenery can do for you. Force you to open your eyes to what else is out there. And in turn introduce you to new ways of doing and being. That's a gift in and of itself.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Now I'm not telling you any of this to convince you to give up your Mac or your iPhone. People who love their Apple gear aren't going to be convinced by an alternative positive vision because they're simply not in the market for one. That's where I was for a long time. Just not interested.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;I'm telling you this in case your Apple relationship isn't quite so hunky dory. In case their recent trajectory and relationship with developers might have been bugging you too. Because it's in that situation you really need to know that the alternatives are not just present, they're &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt;. Their value isn't defined as not-Apple. There's no valor in that.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Linux is wonderful, is flawed, is messy, is beautiful, is nerdy, is different. Android is customizable, is open, is fragmented, is less polished, is experimental. All the pros and the cons are true at the same time. &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;And it's a compelling adventure to discover whether the trade-offs speak to you. Don't be afraid to take the trip, but give it at least two weeks (if not two months!), and don't think of the journey as a way to find the same home in a different place. Be open to a new home, in a new way, in a new place. You might just like it.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>David Heinemeier Hansson</name>
      <email>dhh@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/37611</id>
    <published>2024-06-08T06:16:45Z</published>
    <updated>2024-06-08T06:16:45Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/visions-of-the-future-2e23ff85"/>
    <title>Visions of the future</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;Nothing gets me quite as fired up as discovering the future early and undistributed. That feeling of realizing that something is simply better, and the only reason it hasn't taken off yet is because the world hasn't realized it. It's amazing, and it's how I'm feeling about Linux right now. That &amp;quot;how did I not know it was this good&amp;quot; sensation.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;I felt the same way about the Mac back in 2001. And Ruby in 2003. And company chat with Campfire in 2005. And, fast forward, now with #nobuild, Hotwire, and even exiting the cloud. When I discover a path that seems like a clear shortcut, it doesn't really matter if it's poorly paved at first. As long as it appears to take us somewhere better, laying the bricks and clearing the brush is incidental.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's about seeing that end state. Where what's right in front of us now, rough and unpolished as it may be, can be transformed, if we put in the effort, that inspires me to keep going.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;Yes, half the fun is the adventure. We should always be pushing toward new horizons, even if some of them inevitably will end up in dead ends. But the other half is watching things genuinely compound for the better.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Take web development. It's incredible how much conceptual complexity we've been able to compress in the last decade, and particularly in the last half of a decade. It wasn't just one thing, it was all the things. It was browsers getting better, mobile CPUs getting faster, #nobuild becoming possible, Hotwire showing an alternate route. Each substantial, yes, but together epoch altering. A new dawn.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Following such a sense of wanderlust requires a certain disagreeableness. Even arrogance. A steadfast belief that it's possible that you might actually have found a better way. Whether that turns out to be true or not. You have to believe that it's possible. That the market place of ideas isn't perfectly efficient or perfectly rational. That it hasn't priced it all in, and that you could invest in upcoming concepts for an intellectual profit.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;You're never going to be right about everything, but a life spent without taking at least a few bets on being early on an idea is one not lived to the fullest. Dare a little. Roll the dice every now and then. Come along for an adventure whether its heads or tails.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>David Heinemeier Hansson</name>
      <email>dhh@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/37584</id>
    <published>2024-06-06T14:29:39Z</published>
    <updated>2024-06-06T14:29:40Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/introducing-omakub-354db366"/>
    <title>Introducing Omakub</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;Linux can look and feel so good, but it often doesn't out of the box. It's almost like there's a rite of passage in certain parts of the community where becoming an expert in the intricacies of every tool and its theming is required to prove you're a proper nerd. I think that's a bit silly, so I created &lt;a href="https://omakub.org"&gt;Omakub: An opinionated web developer setup for Ubuntu&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;Omakub turns a fresh Ubuntu installation into a fully-configured, beautiful, and modern web development system by running a single command. No need to write bespoke configs for every essential tool just to get started or to be up on all the latest command-line tools. Omakub is an opinionated take on what Linux can be at its best.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Omakub includes a curated set of applications and tools that one might discover through hours of watching YouTube, reading blogs, or just stumbling around Linux internet. All so someone coming straight from a platform like Windows or the Mac can immediately start enjoying a ready-made system, without having to do any configuration and curation legwork at all.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;This isn’t a project for someone already versed in the intricacies of nixOS or relishing a fresh install of Arch. It’s using vanilla Ubuntu because that’s one of the most widely adopted Linux distributions, and one that is even a pre-install option from many computer vendors. But while Ubuntu has a great package manager in apt, many of the tools that developers want either haven’t been packaged, need more recent versions than what has been frozen in the LTS, or need actions post-install necessary for the best operation. Omakub includes all those scripts needed.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;But package management is only half the battle of getting a great development experience going on Linux. The other half lies in the dotfiles that control the configuration. Linux gets great power from how customizable it is, but that also presents a paradox of choice and a tall learning curve. Having good, curated defaults that integrate all the many tools in a coherent feel and look can help more developers acquire a taste for Linux, which they may then later inspire a fully bespoke setup (or not!).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Nothing in Omakub provides solutions to problems you couldn’t also solve a million other ways. The main benefit is in The Omakase Spirit. The idea that an entire setup experience can benefit from being tailored upfront by someone with strong opinions about what works and looks good together. This doesn’t make the choices necessarily better than other choices. Linux has inspired a million options for a million tastes. That’s great and worthy of celebration. But there’s a large constituency of developers who are more than willing to trade ultimate bespoke customization for a cohesive package of goods, at least until they understand what all the options are and have fully bought into making the switch to Linux.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Omakub is for all these future Linux users.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-gallery attachment-gallery--2"&gt;
    &lt;figure class="attachment attachment--preview attachment--lightboxable attachment--png"&gt;
      &lt;a download="Screenshot from 2024-06-05 12-33-01.png" title="Download Screenshot from 2024-06-05 12-33-01.png" data-click-proxy-target="lightbox_link_blob_1687150896" href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/354db366/blobs/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaHNLd2N3NFk5ayIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoiYmxvYl9pZCJ9fQ==--0af57d73de98f8f0941a3e37c5a9d4438e77dcc5/Screenshot%20from%202024-06-05%2012-33-01.png?disposition=attachment"&gt;
        &lt;img src="https://world.hey.com/dhh/354db366/representations/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaHNLd2N3NFk5ayIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoiYmxvYl9pZCJ9fQ==--0af57d73de98f8f0941a3e37c5a9d4438e77dcc5/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaDdDam9MWm05eWJXRjBTU0lJY0c1bkJqb0dSVlE2RkhKbGMybDZaVjkwYjE5c2FXMXBkRnNIYVFJZ0Eya0NXQUk2REhGMVlXeHBkSGxwU3pvTGJHOWhaR1Z5ZXdZNkNYQmhaMlV3T2cxamIyRnNaWE5qWlZRPSIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoidmFyaWF0aW9uIn19--5b3d546d4a851deaf90c0a36232de4bed8a44df9/Screenshot%20from%202024-06-05%2012-33-01.png" alt="Screenshot from 2024-06-05 12-33-01.png" srcset="https://world.hey.com/dhh/354db366/representations/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaHNLd2N3NFk5ayIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoiYmxvYl9pZCJ9fQ==--0af57d73de98f8f0941a3e37c5a9d4438e77dcc5/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaDdDam9MWm05eWJXRjBTU0lJY0c1bkJqb0dSVlE2RkhKbGMybDZaVjkwYjE5c2FXMXBkRnNIYVFKQUJta0NzQVE2REhGMVlXeHBkSGxwUVRvTGJHOWhaR1Z5ZXdZNkNYQmhaMlV3T2cxamIyRnNaWE5qWlZRPSIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoidmFyaWF0aW9uIn19--c8afdeb1970d74bb39f9e56f9caf9a80812fedb2/Screenshot%20from%202024-06-05%2012-33-01.png 2x, https://world.hey.com/dhh/354db366/representations/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaHNLd2N3NFk5ayIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoiYmxvYl9pZCJ9fQ==--0af57d73de98f8f0941a3e37c5a9d4438e77dcc5/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaDdDam9MWm05eWJXRjBTU0lJY0c1bkJqb0dSVlE2RkhKbGMybDZaVjkwYjE5c2FXMXBkRnNIYVFKZ0NXa0NDQWM2REhGMVlXeHBkSGxwUERvTGJHOWhaR1Z5ZXdZNkNYQmhaMlV3T2cxamIyRnNaWE5qWlZRPSIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoidmFyaWF0aW9uIn19--e4d47493071e7dfc7a48a7021dc4d66e1a58e378/Screenshot%20from%202024-06-05%2012-33-01.png 3x" decoding="async" loading="lazy"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;  &lt;figure class="attachment attachment--preview attachment--lightboxable attachment--png"&gt;
      &lt;a download="gruvbox.png" title="Download gruvbox.png" data-click-proxy-target="lightbox_link_blob_1687151234" href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/354db366/blobs/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaHNLd2VDNG85ayIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoiYmxvYl9pZCJ9fQ==--8b6fc626d5ec34def362c286e2aa3267d60dce10/gruvbox.png?disposition=attachment"&gt;
        &lt;img src="https://world.hey.com/dhh/354db366/representations/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaHNLd2VDNG85ayIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoiYmxvYl9pZCJ9fQ==--8b6fc626d5ec34def362c286e2aa3267d60dce10/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaDdDam9MWm05eWJXRjBTU0lJY0c1bkJqb0dSVlE2RkhKbGMybDZaVjkwYjE5c2FXMXBkRnNIYVFJZ0Eya0NXQUk2REhGMVlXeHBkSGxwU3pvTGJHOWhaR1Z5ZXdZNkNYQmhaMlV3T2cxamIyRnNaWE5qWlZRPSIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoidmFyaWF0aW9uIn19--5b3d546d4a851deaf90c0a36232de4bed8a44df9/gruvbox.png" alt="gruvbox.png" srcset="https://world.hey.com/dhh/354db366/representations/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaHNLd2VDNG85ayIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoiYmxvYl9pZCJ9fQ==--8b6fc626d5ec34def362c286e2aa3267d60dce10/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaDdDam9MWm05eWJXRjBTU0lJY0c1bkJqb0dSVlE2RkhKbGMybDZaVjkwYjE5c2FXMXBkRnNIYVFKQUJta0NzQVE2REhGMVlXeHBkSGxwUVRvTGJHOWhaR1Z5ZXdZNkNYQmhaMlV3T2cxamIyRnNaWE5qWlZRPSIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoidmFyaWF0aW9uIn19--c8afdeb1970d74bb39f9e56f9caf9a80812fedb2/gruvbox.png 2x, https://world.hey.com/dhh/354db366/representations/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaHNLd2VDNG85ayIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoiYmxvYl9pZCJ9fQ==--8b6fc626d5ec34def362c286e2aa3267d60dce10/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaDdDam9MWm05eWJXRjBTU0lJY0c1bkJqb0dSVlE2RkhKbGMybDZaVjkwYjE5c2FXMXBkRnNIYVFKZ0NXa0NDQWM2REhGMVlXeHBkSGxwUERvTGJHOWhaR1Z5ZXdZNkNYQmhaMlV3T2cxamIyRnNaWE5qWlZRPSIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoidmFyaWF0aW9uIn19--e4d47493071e7dfc7a48a7021dc4d66e1a58e378/gruvbox.png 3x" decoding="async" loading="lazy"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div class="attachment-gallery attachment-gallery--2"&gt;
    &lt;figure class="attachment attachment--preview attachment--lightboxable attachment--png"&gt;
      &lt;a download="everforest.png" title="Download everforest.png" data-click-proxy-target="lightbox_link_blob_1687151487" href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/354db366/blobs/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaHNLd2QvNDQ5ayIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoiYmxvYl9pZCJ9fQ==--49fd171e7a7a93525cf8f82e27573a5743178e3a/everforest.png?disposition=attachment"&gt;
        &lt;img src="https://world.hey.com/dhh/354db366/representations/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaHNLd2QvNDQ5ayIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoiYmxvYl9pZCJ9fQ==--49fd171e7a7a93525cf8f82e27573a5743178e3a/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaDdDam9MWm05eWJXRjBTU0lJY0c1bkJqb0dSVlE2RkhKbGMybDZaVjkwYjE5c2FXMXBkRnNIYVFJZ0Eya0NXQUk2REhGMVlXeHBkSGxwU3pvTGJHOWhaR1Z5ZXdZNkNYQmhaMlV3T2cxamIyRnNaWE5qWlZRPSIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoidmFyaWF0aW9uIn19--5b3d546d4a851deaf90c0a36232de4bed8a44df9/everforest.png" alt="everforest.png" srcset="https://world.hey.com/dhh/354db366/representations/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaHNLd2QvNDQ5ayIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoiYmxvYl9pZCJ9fQ==--49fd171e7a7a93525cf8f82e27573a5743178e3a/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaDdDam9MWm05eWJXRjBTU0lJY0c1bkJqb0dSVlE2RkhKbGMybDZaVjkwYjE5c2FXMXBkRnNIYVFKQUJta0NzQVE2REhGMVlXeHBkSGxwUVRvTGJHOWhaR1Z5ZXdZNkNYQmhaMlV3T2cxamIyRnNaWE5qWlZRPSIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoidmFyaWF0aW9uIn19--c8afdeb1970d74bb39f9e56f9caf9a80812fedb2/everforest.png 2x, https://world.hey.com/dhh/354db366/representations/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaHNLd2QvNDQ5ayIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoiYmxvYl9pZCJ9fQ==--49fd171e7a7a93525cf8f82e27573a5743178e3a/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaDdDam9MWm05eWJXRjBTU0lJY0c1bkJqb0dSVlE2RkhKbGMybDZaVjkwYjE5c2FXMXBkRnNIYVFKZ0NXa0NDQWM2REhGMVlXeHBkSGxwUERvTGJHOWhaR1Z5ZXdZNkNYQmhaMlV3T2cxamIyRnNaWE5qWlZRPSIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoidmFyaWF0aW9uIn19--e4d47493071e7dfc7a48a7021dc4d66e1a58e378/everforest.png 3x" decoding="async" loading="lazy"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;  &lt;figure class="attachment attachment--preview attachment--lightboxable attachment--png"&gt;
      &lt;a download="rosepine.png" title="Download rosepine.png" data-click-proxy-target="lightbox_link_blob_1687151742" href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/354db366/blobs/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaHNLd2QrNUk5ayIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoiYmxvYl9pZCJ9fQ==--ab1f13914eeaaf8c81398767884716ce793f605b/rosepine.png?disposition=attachment"&gt;
        &lt;img src="https://world.hey.com/dhh/354db366/representations/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaHNLd2QrNUk5ayIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoiYmxvYl9pZCJ9fQ==--ab1f13914eeaaf8c81398767884716ce793f605b/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaDdDam9MWm05eWJXRjBTU0lJY0c1bkJqb0dSVlE2RkhKbGMybDZaVjkwYjE5c2FXMXBkRnNIYVFJZ0Eya0NXQUk2REhGMVlXeHBkSGxwU3pvTGJHOWhaR1Z5ZXdZNkNYQmhaMlV3T2cxamIyRnNaWE5qWlZRPSIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoidmFyaWF0aW9uIn19--5b3d546d4a851deaf90c0a36232de4bed8a44df9/rosepine.png" alt="rosepine.png" srcset="https://world.hey.com/dhh/354db366/representations/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaHNLd2QrNUk5ayIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoiYmxvYl9pZCJ9fQ==--ab1f13914eeaaf8c81398767884716ce793f605b/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaDdDam9MWm05eWJXRjBTU0lJY0c1bkJqb0dSVlE2RkhKbGMybDZaVjkwYjE5c2FXMXBkRnNIYVFKQUJta0NzQVE2REhGMVlXeHBkSGxwUVRvTGJHOWhaR1Z5ZXdZNkNYQmhaMlV3T2cxamIyRnNaWE5qWlZRPSIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoidmFyaWF0aW9uIn19--c8afdeb1970d74bb39f9e56f9caf9a80812fedb2/rosepine.png 2x, https://world.hey.com/dhh/354db366/representations/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaHNLd2QrNUk5ayIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoiYmxvYl9pZCJ9fQ==--ab1f13914eeaaf8c81398767884716ce793f605b/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaDdDam9MWm05eWJXRjBTU0lJY0c1bkJqb0dSVlE2RkhKbGMybDZaVjkwYjE5c2FXMXBkRnNIYVFKZ0NXa0NDQWM2REhGMVlXeHBkSGxwUERvTGJHOWhaR1Z5ZXdZNkNYQmhaMlV3T2cxamIyRnNaWE5qWlZRPSIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoidmFyaWF0aW9uIn19--e4d47493071e7dfc7a48a7021dc4d66e1a58e378/rosepine.png 3x" decoding="async" loading="lazy"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>David Heinemeier Hansson</name>
      <email>dhh@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/37500</id>
    <published>2024-06-02T21:56:33Z</published>
    <updated>2024-06-03T17:32:58Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/why-i-retired-from-the-tech-crusades-107a51ea"/>
    <title>Why I retired from the tech crusades</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;When &lt;a href="https://rubyonrails.org/"&gt;Ruby on Rails&lt;/a&gt; was launched over twenty years ago, I was a twenty-some young programmer convinced that anyone who gave my stack a try would accept its universal superiority for solving The Web Problem. So I pursued the path of the crusade, attempting to convert the unenlightened masses by the edge of a pointed argument.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;And for a long time, I thought that's what had worked. That this was why Ruby on Rails took off, became one of the most popular full-stack web frameworks of all time, inspired countless clones, and created hundreds of billions in enterprise value for companies built on it. But I was wrong. It wasn't the crusade that did it.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Since those early days, I've talked to thousands of programmers who adopted Ruby on Rails back then, and do you know what virtually every one of them cite? That &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Gzj723LkRJY"&gt;original 15-minute blog video&lt;/a&gt;. Which didn't contain a single comparison to other named solutions or specifically pointed arguments against alternatives. It just showed what you could do with Ruby on Rails, and the A/B comparison automatically ran inside the mind of every programmer who was exposed to that.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;That's what did it. Showing something great, and letting those who weren't happy with their current situation become inspired to check it out. Because those are the only people who are able to convert to your cause anyway. I've never seen someone who was head'over'heels in love with, say, functional programming be won over by arguments for objected-oriented programming.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;You simply can't dunk someone into submission, and it's usually counterproductive if you try. But you can absolutely attract people who aren't happy with their current circumstances to give an alternative a chance, if you simply show them how it works, and allow them to conclude by themselves how it would make their programming life better.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;What I've also come to realize is that &lt;a href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/programming-types-and-mindsets-5b8490bc"&gt;programmers come in many different intellectual shapes and sizes&lt;/a&gt;. Some of those shapes will click with functional programming, and that'll be their path to passion. Others will click with vanilla JavaScript, and be relieved to give up the build pipelines. Others still will find their spirit in Go. This is great. Seriously. The fact that working for the web allows for such diverse ecosystem choices is an incredible feature, not a bug.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;I found my life's work and passion in Ruby. I have friends who've found theirs in Python or Elixir or PHP or Go or even JavaScript. That's wonderful! And that's really all I want for you. I want you to be happy. I want you to find just that right language that opens your mind to the beautiful game of coding in your most compatible mode of conception, as Ruby did for me.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;This is not the same as just saying &amp;quot;everything has trade-offs, use what works best&amp;quot;. That to me is a bit of a cop out. There is no universal set of trade-offs that'll make something objectively &amp;quot;work best&amp;quot;. Half the programming conundrum lies in connecting to an enduring source of motivation. I wouldn't be a happy camper if  I had to spend my days programming Rust (but I LOVE so many of the tools coming out of that community by people who DO enjoy just that).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;It also doesn't mean we should give up on technical discussions of advantages or disadvantages, but I think those are generally more effective when performed in the style of &amp;quot;here's what I like, why I like it, so look at my code, my outcomes, and see if it tickles your fancy too&amp;quot;.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Programming is a beautiful game. I would give up all the fancy cars I have in a heartbeat, if I was made to choose between them and programming. The intellectual stimulation, the occasional high from hitting The Zone, is such a concrete illustration of Coco Chanel's &amp;quot;the best things in life are free, the second best things are very expensive&amp;quot;. Programming is one of those &amp;quot;best things&amp;quot; that is virtually free to everyone in the Western world (and increasingly so everywhere else too). &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;So let's play that beautiful game to the best of our ability, in the position that flatters our conceptual capacities the most, and create some wonderful code.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>David Heinemeier Hansson</name>
      <email>dhh@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/37311</id>
    <published>2024-05-24T16:58:09Z</published>
    <updated>2024-05-24T20:52:55Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/linux-as-the-new-developer-default-at-37signals-ef0823b7"/>
    <title>Linux as the new developer default at 37signals</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;For over twenty years, the Mac was the default at &lt;a href="https://37signals.com/"&gt;37signals&lt;/a&gt;. For designers, programmers, support, and everyone else. That mono culture had some clear advantages, like being able to run &lt;a href="https://www.kandji.io/mdm/start/product/?igaag=140078782775&amp;amp;igaat=&amp;amp;igacm=17933802411&amp;amp;igacr=694321941503&amp;amp;igakw=kandji&amp;amp;igamt=e&amp;amp;igant=g&amp;amp;tm=tt&amp;amp;ap=gads&amp;amp;aaid=adauVrFKpawwA&amp;amp;utm_feeditemid=&amp;amp;utm_device=c&amp;amp;utm_medium=paid&amp;amp;utm_source=google&amp;amp;utm_campaign=ch.sem_tgt.kandji-brand_mt.exact_rgn.namer.t1&amp;amp;utm_term=kandji&amp;amp;utm_content=694321941503&amp;amp;hsa_acc=1685973693&amp;amp;hsa_cam=17933802411&amp;amp;hsa_grp=140078782775&amp;amp;hsa_ad=694321941503&amp;amp;hsa_src=g&amp;amp;hsa_tgt=kwd-618499492764&amp;amp;hsa_kw=kandji&amp;amp;hsa_mt=e&amp;amp;hsa_net=adwords&amp;amp;hsa_ver=3&amp;amp;cq_sr=google_ads&amp;amp;cq_cmp=17933802411&amp;amp;cq_con=140078782775&amp;amp;cq_plac=&amp;amp;cq_net=g&amp;amp;cq_plt=gp&amp;amp;gad_source=1&amp;amp;gclid=CjwKCAjw9cCyBhBzEiwAJTUWNcaLp0qUytqC2FHMy9B4InQUqgjvKLWjP8cK7cnLr-ryMyfJpzqyWhoCTaAQAvD_BwE"&gt;Kandji&lt;/a&gt; and macOS-specific setup scripts. But it certainly also had its disadvantages, like dealing with &lt;a href="https://signalvnoise.com/svn3/the-macbook-keyboard-fiasco-is-surely-worse-than-apple-thinks/"&gt;Apple's awful reliability years&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/you-can-own-more-than-one-type-of-computer-73439146"&gt;being cut off&lt;/a&gt; from seeing how half our Basecamp customer base saw by default (since they're on Windows!). Either way, it's over. Apple is no longer the exclusive default at 37signals. Going forward, we're working to make Linux the default for developers and system operators (and welcoming Windows back in the mix for accounting/marketing). &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;I've personally been having a blast over the last few months digging deeper and deeper into the Linux rabbit hole, and it's been a delight discovering just how good its become as developer platform. Not one without its flaws, obviously, but an incredible proposition none the less.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;This has left me with little interest in going back to a commercial operating system as a daily development driver. My entire career has been spent in the service and sun of open source, both as a contributor and a beneficiary, and closing the loop with a desktop operating system is very satisfying.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Default doesn't mean edict, though. First of all, we have a great mobile team that simply needs to be on Apple hardware to develop for Apple platforms. That's not changing. Neither is the fact that some people will have a strong personal preference to stick with the Mac. Totally fine too.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;But defaults still matter. Along with assumptions about what's supported and how well. And changing our default to Linux sets a new tone, as well as affords us the institutional weight to support companies like &lt;a href="https://frame.work/"&gt;Framework&lt;/a&gt; with our business. I love voting with my dollars for more of a future I'd like to see, and Framework represents just that.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;The end result will be a company that has people running Mac, Windows, and Linux. Which is great from both the perspective of living how your customers do, but also escaping the trapped feeling of a mono culture built around an Apple that we, and many other developers, are &lt;a href="https://www.hey.com/apple/"&gt;increasingly at odds with&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;None of this has to be binary. Hate/love. Yes/no. Sure, Apple has evolved into a company that's much harder to recommend for people who care about the future of computing, but they still make great hardware, and the M-chip revolution will continue to benefit anyone who likes computers.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;So I haven't crushed my MacBook in defiance. We won't be wholesaling out our existing fleet of Apple machines either. But going forward, we'll spend more of our money and attention on platforms that align better with &lt;a href="https://37signals.com/01"&gt;the independence&lt;/a&gt; and freedom we so cherish in all other aspects of our business.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;The year of Linux on the desktop. Who would have thought!&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;  &lt;figure class="attachment attachment--preview attachment--lightboxable attachment--png"&gt;
      &lt;a download="linux-desktop.png" title="Download linux-desktop.png" data-click-proxy-target="lightbox_link_blob_1671059107" href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/ef0823b7/blobs/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaHNLd2VqVnBwaiIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoiYmxvYl9pZCJ9fQ==--3821242466e5397e576af6fc771ff62889dc8449/linux-desktop.png?disposition=attachment"&gt;
        &lt;img src="https://world.hey.com/dhh/ef0823b7/representations/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaHNLd2VqVnBwaiIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoiYmxvYl9pZCJ9fQ==--3821242466e5397e576af6fc771ff62889dc8449/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaDdDam9MWm05eWJXRjBTU0lJY0c1bkJqb0dSVlE2RkhKbGMybDZaVjkwYjE5c2FXMXBkRnNIYVFLQUIya0NBQVU2REhGMVlXeHBkSGxwU3pvTGJHOWhaR1Z5ZXdZNkNYQmhaMlV3T2cxamIyRnNaWE5qWlZRPSIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoidmFyaWF0aW9uIn19--946116ea0c454412635aa7309bd9472bf633014c/linux-desktop.png" alt="linux-desktop.png" srcset="https://world.hey.com/dhh/ef0823b7/representations/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaHNLd2VqVnBwaiIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoiYmxvYl9pZCJ9fQ==--3821242466e5397e576af6fc771ff62889dc8449/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaDdDam9MWm05eWJXRjBTU0lJY0c1bkJqb0dSVlE2RkhKbGMybDZaVjkwYjE5c2FXMXBkRnNIYVFJQUQya0NBQW82REhGMVlXeHBkSGxwUVRvTGJHOWhaR1Z5ZXdZNkNYQmhaMlV3T2cxamIyRnNaWE5qWlZRPSIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoidmFyaWF0aW9uIn19--8c0bbbd8bfe72a73b222ec1c20265f8631973dc9/linux-desktop.png 2x, https://world.hey.com/dhh/ef0823b7/representations/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaHNLd2VqVnBwaiIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoiYmxvYl9pZCJ9fQ==--3821242466e5397e576af6fc771ff62889dc8449/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaDdDam9MWm05eWJXRjBTU0lJY0c1bkJqb0dSVlE2RkhKbGMybDZaVjkwYjE5c2FXMXBkRnNIYVFLQUZta0NBQTg2REhGMVlXeHBkSGxwUERvTGJHOWhaR1Z5ZXdZNkNYQmhaMlV3T2cxamIyRnNaWE5qWlZRPSIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoidmFyaWF0aW9uIn19--d2fed6b5089e475a3013538949ec7f311ac6e345/linux-desktop.png 3x" decoding="async" loading="lazy"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>David Heinemeier Hansson</name>
      <email>dhh@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/37217</id>
    <published>2024-05-20T19:46:14Z</published>
    <updated>2024-05-20T19:46:14Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/beautiful-motivations-6fef7c73"/>
    <title>Beautiful motivations</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;Programmers are often skeptical of aesthetics because they frequently associate it with veneering. A thin sheen of flashy marketing design covering up for a rotten or deficient product. Something that looks good from afar, but reveals itself to be a disappointing imitation up close. They're right to be skeptical. Cheap veneers are the worst. But discarding the value of aesthetic on behalf of cheap imitations is a mistake.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Not just because truly beautiful objects and concepts inevitably reveal a deeper and designed experience. That's the whole &amp;quot;I'm writing you a long letter because I didn't have time to write you a short one&amp;quot;. Making something beautiful takes extra steps. Steps that are commonly also associated with extra care the rest of the creation.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;No, the primary reason I appreciate aesthetics so much is its power to motivate. And motivation is the rare fuel that powers all the big leaps I've ever taken in my career and with my projects and products. It's not time, it's even attention. It's motivation. And I've found that nothing quite motivates me like using and creating beautiful things.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;I don't think that would come as any surprise to people of the past. The history of creation is in part a tale of pursuing beautiful outcomes and rewards. But in our age, we've managed to deconstruct and problematize so much of what is self-evidently beautiful that it's harder to take the chase for granted.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's in the context of this age that I labor for programmers to rediscover beauty. Beautiful code, beautiful patterns, beautiful tools. Not to create a single, monoculture of aesthetics. That's never going to happen. But to elevate the work of making things look not just good, but sublime. To revel in it, to celebrate it.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;And beauty isn't binary. It's the journey of a thousand little decisions and investments in making something marginally prettier than it was before. To resist the urge to just make it work, and not stop until you make it shine. Not for anyone else, even, although others will undoubtedly appreciate your care. But for yourself, your own motivation, and your own mission.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>David Heinemeier Hansson</name>
      <email>dhh@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/37161</id>
    <published>2024-05-17T19:29:36Z</published>
    <updated>2024-05-17T19:29:36Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/system-tests-have-failed-d90af718"/>
    <title>System tests have failed</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;When we introduced a &lt;a href="https://guides.rubyonrails.org/5_1_release_notes.html#system-tests"&gt;default setup for system tests&lt;/a&gt; in Rails 5.1 back in 2016, I had high hopes. In theory, system tests, which drive a headless browser through your actual interface, offer greater confidence that the entire machine is working as it ought. And because it runs in a black-box fashion, it should be more resilient to implementation changes. But I'm sad to report that I have not found any of this to be true in practice. System tests remain as slow, brittle, and full of false negatives as they did a decade ago.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;I'm sure there are many reasons for this state of malaise. Browsers are complicated, UI driven by JavaScript is prone to timing issues, and figuring out WHY a black-box test has failed is often surprisingly difficult. But the bottom line for me is that system tests no longer seem worth the effort the majority of the time. Or said another way, I've wasted far more time getting system tests to work reliably than I have seen dividends from bugs caught.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;Which gets to the heart of why we automate testing. We do it for the quick feedback loop on changes, we do it to catch regressions, but most of all, we do it to become confident that the system works. These are all valid goals, but that doesn't mean system testing is the best way to fulfill them.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Now I'm not advocating you throw out all your system tests. Just, you know, probably most of them. System tests work well for the top-level smoke test. The end-to-end'ness has a tendency to catch not problems with the domain model or business logic, but some configuration or interaction that's preventing the system from loading correctly at all. Catching that early and cheaply is good.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;The stickiest point, however, is not testing business logic, which model and controller tests do better and cheaper, but testing UI logic. Which means testing JavaScript. And I'll say I'm not sure we're there yet on the automated front. &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;The method that gives me the most confidence that my UI logic is good to go is not system tests, but human tests. Literally clicking around in a real browser by hand. Because half the time UI testing is not just about &amp;quot;does it work&amp;quot; but also &amp;quot;does it feel right&amp;quot;. No automation can tell you that.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;HEY today has some 300-odd system tests. We're going through a grand review to cut that number way down. The sunk cost fallacy has kept us running this brittle, cumbersome suite for too long. Time to cut our losses, reduce system tests to a much smaller part of the confidence equation, and &lt;a href="https://signalvnoise.com/svn3/the-value-of-human-exploratory-testing/"&gt;embrace the human element of system testing&lt;/a&gt;. Maybe one day we can hand that task over to AI, but as of today, I think we're better off dropping the automation.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>David Heinemeier Hansson</name>
      <email>dhh@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/37152</id>
    <published>2024-05-17T15:25:28Z</published>
    <updated>2024-05-17T16:56:20Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/paranoia-and-desperation-in-the-ai-gold-rush-33042dbc"/>
    <title>Paranoia and desperation in the AI gold rush</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;I've never seen so much paranoia in technology about missing out on The Next Big Thing as with AI. Companies seem less excited about the prospects than they are petrified that its going to kill them. Maybe that fear is justified, maybe it's not, but what's incontestable is the kind of desperation it's leading to. Case in point: Slack.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;So &lt;a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=40383978&amp;amp;ref=thestack.technology"&gt;Salesforce just announced that they'll be training their Slack AI models on people's private messages, files, and other content&lt;/a&gt;. And they're going to do so by default, lest you send them a specially formatted email to &lt;a href="mailto:feedback@slack.com"&gt;feedback@slack.com&lt;/a&gt;. I mean, really, feedback? It's the kind of process that invites a quip about some knuckle-sandwich feedback to their face. But I digress. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Presumably this is because some Salesforce executives got the great idea in a brainstorming sesh that the way to catch up to the big players in AI is by just ignoring privacy concerns all together. If you can't beat the likes of OpenAI in scanning the sum of public human knowledge, maybe you can beat them by scanning all the confidential conversations about new product strategies, lay-off plans that haven't been announced yet, or private financial projections for 2025?&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;I mean imagine the delight some CEO might feel when they start typing out the announcement to lay off 30% of the workforce, and Slack autocompletes the text with the most anodyne distillation from five competitors doing the same? All you have to do is edit out, say, Asana in your layoff completion, and voila, you'll have saved at least 8 minutes typing out the corporate slop yourself.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Whether the vision of that gleams bright or dystopian probably depends on how well your inner compass is tuned to the kind of AI KPIs pushing product managers in charge of acquired chat products at large tech companies.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;But the more interesting point to me is what this says about the broad paranoia and desperation in the AI gold rush. Things are moving fast enough that we'll probably see more such flagrant transgressions of trust and privacy, if there's even a sliver of a chance that it can provide an edge in the race for a better chatbot. Buckle up!&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>David Heinemeier Hansson</name>
      <email>dhh@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/37141</id>
    <published>2024-05-16T19:41:37Z</published>
    <updated>2024-05-16T19:41:37Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/open-source-is-neither-a-community-nor-a-democracy-606abdab"/>
    <title>Open source is neither a community nor a democracy</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;Using open source software does not entitle you to a vote on the direction of the project. The gift you've received is the software itself and the freedom of use granted by the license. That's it, and this ought to be straight forward, but I repeatedly see that it is not (no matter &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/richhickey/1563cddea1002958f96e7ba9519972d9"&gt;how often it is repeated&lt;/a&gt;). And I think the problem stems from the word &amp;quot;community&amp;quot;, which implies a democratic decision-making process that never actually existed in the open source world.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;First of all, community implies that we're all participating on some degree of equal footing in the work required to further the welfare of the group. But that's not how the majority of open source projects are run. They're usually run by a small group of core contributors who take on the responsibility to advance the project, review patches, and guard the integrity of the vision. The division of labor isn't even close to be egalitarian. It's almost always distinctly elitist.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;That's good! Yes, elitism is good, when it comes to open source. You absolutely want projects to be driven by the people who show up to do the work, demonstrate their superior dedication and competence, and are thus responsible for keeping the gift factory churning out new updates, features, and releases. Productive effort is the correct moral basis of power in these projects. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;But this elitism is also the root of entitlement tension. What makes you think you're better than Me/Us/The Community in setting the direction for this project?? Wouldn't it be more &lt;em&gt;fair&lt;/em&gt;, if we ran this on democratic consensus?? And it's hard to answer these question in a polite way that doesn't aggravate the tension or offend liberal sensibilities (in the broad historic sense of that word -- not present political alignments).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;So we usually skirt around the truth. That not all participants in an open source project contribute equally in neither volume nor value, and this discrepancy is the basis of the hierarchical nature of most projects. It is not, and never will be, one user, one vote. That is, it will never be democratic. And this is good!&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;The democratic ideals are fulfilled by the fact that open source is free and full of alternatives. Don't like how they're running a given project? Use one of the usual countless alternatives. Or start your own! Here, you can even use the work of a million projects that came before you as a base for doing new work.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;But the reason this doesn't resolve the tension is that it still relies on showing up and doing the work. And there just so happens to be far fewer individuals willing and capable of doing that than there are individuals who wish they had a say on the direction of their favorite software.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;You can't solve that tension, only acknowledge it. I've dealt with it for literally twenty years with my work on Rails and a million other open source projects. There's an ever-latent instinct in a substantial subset of open source users who will continuously rear itself to question why it's the people who do the most work or deliver the most value or start the most projects that get to have the largest say.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;And when people talk about open source burnout, it's often related to this entitlement syndrome. Although it's frequently misdiagnosed as a problem of compensation. As if begging for a few dollars would somehow make the entitlement problem bearable. I don't think it would. Programmers frequently turn to the joy of open source exactly because it exists outside &lt;a href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/i-won-t-let-you-pay-me-for-my-open-source-d7cf4568"&gt;the normal employment dynamics of quid-pro-quo&lt;/a&gt;. That's the relief.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;I frequently argue that open source is best seen as &lt;a href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/the-open-source-gift-exchange-2171e0f0"&gt;a gift exchange&lt;/a&gt;, since that puts the emphasis on how to react as receiver of gifts. But if you're going to use another word as an alternative to community, I suggest you look at &amp;quot;ecosystem&amp;quot;. Ecosystems aren't egalitarian. There are big fish and little fish. Sometimes the relationships are symbiotic, but they're also potentially parasitic.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;But whatever word you choose, you'd do well to remember that open source is first and foremost a method of collaboration between programmers who show up to do the work. Not an entitlement program for petulant users to get free stuff or a seat at the table where decisions are made.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>David Heinemeier Hansson</name>
      <email>dhh@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/37109</id>
    <published>2024-05-14T21:57:54Z</published>
    <updated>2024-05-14T21:57:54Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/meta-is-shutting-down-workplace-3e24bca5"/>
    <title>Meta is shutting down Workplace</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;The saying &amp;quot;nobody ever got fired for buying IBM&amp;quot; is at its essence about risk management. The traditional wisdom goes that if you buy from a big company, you're going to be safe. It may be more expensive, but big companies project an image of stability and reliability, so buying their wares is seen as the prudent choice. Except, it isn't. Certainly not any more. &lt;a href="https://www.fastcompany.com/91125164/meta-shuts-down-workplace-app-to-on-ai-and-metaverse"&gt;Meta killing Workplace&lt;/a&gt; is merely exhibit #49667.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Any company that hitched their wagon to Workplace just got served with an eviction notice. In a about a year, the data will go read-only, and shortly after that, it's game over. Now companies from Spotify to McDonalds, along with millions of others, have to scramble to find an alternative. Simply because Meta can't be bothered to maintain a platform that's merely used by millions when their consumer business is used by billions.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;This, right here, is the risk of buying anything from big tech like Meta and Google. Their main ad-based cash cows are so fantastically profitable that whether it's the millions of paying accounts on Workplace or the millions of live websites &lt;a href="https://9to5google.com/2023/06/15/google-domains-squarespace/"&gt;once hosted by Google Domains&lt;/a&gt;, it all just pales in comparison, and is thus one strategy rotation away from being labeled &amp;quot;non-core&amp;quot; and killed off.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Buying from big isn't the sure bet they want you to believe. Buy from someone who actually needs your business to make the wheels go round.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>David Heinemeier Hansson</name>
      <email>dhh@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/37108</id>
    <published>2024-05-14T17:51:52Z</published>
    <updated>2024-05-14T17:51:52Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/the-endangered-state-of-normality-d632a7fe"/>
    <title>The endangered state of normality</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;When I was growing up in the 80s and 90s, I had friends who were socially awkward nerds, friends who were cool but didn't like school at all, friends who were good at school but couldn't muster the will to finish their math homework, and friends who were tomboys. None of these kids ever got a diagnosis. They were all well within the spectrum of what constituted &amp;quot;normal&amp;quot; back then. Today all of them would likely have acquired some label of pathology because nobody seems to qualify (or desire to be seen) as being normal these days.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;This is the natural consequence of &amp;quot;centering the margins&amp;quot;. Of making it socially desirable to be not normal and low status to be regular. And it's happening across everything from gender expression to neurodiversity. There's cachet of cool to be had in identifying with some margin. Preferably one that can claim to be oppressed by society via heteronormativity or neurotypicality or other big words for &amp;quot;normal&amp;quot;.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;And, as Abigail Shrier documents in &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Bad-Therapy-Kids-Arent-Growing-ebook/dp/B0CBYHTV2D/ref=sr_1_1?crid=22RG21IGAGKAZ&amp;amp;dib=eyJ2IjoiMSJ9.H3z23_Pg5Wj4kGThzo8OhuIcN7zfz70TA_UxvgwN8RFOsfy7D8zGzvSb6HRxztXDqOsxIhOQUWFluEpLXoRQziVIAplJqAj5JNHJkxGl3T00DVfp-IlhkmpQQ2QLhK0ToF3RMp7ZpmVY9jNlQoZsPOSgRjF26seMWHZLxYn9naFzcaTFPHFKIam67AUkbxq-BcFmS2ukFsWgL2zk-Ey_f32I8BM-cmd7fZ_2-BaN7-g.wSYskZ4lnl9G4nxPP5Rpxf8H0lgMwQRLyZyjXkXZC9A"&gt;Bad Therapy&lt;/a&gt;, there's a large industry of therapists and other &amp;quot;mental health professionals&amp;quot; eager to accommodate this flight to the margins. Eager to supply the diagnosis, the pills, the reassurance of how every phase of experimentation or misbehavior can be explained by some big word of pathology.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;I think we've given up on something important in this pursuit of individuality through the spectrum of marginalization. When fitting is less about having the right brand of backpack and more about having some medical prescription.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;Whatever is at play, I think we're better off re-expanding the definition of normal  to fit a much broader spectrum of quirky, weird, and natural varieties of humans. Fewer labels, reserved for far more severe predicaments, and fewer interventions, left for those where the risks of medicalized action far outweighs the risk of iatrogenic treatment.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>David Heinemeier Hansson</name>
      <email>dhh@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/37029</id>
    <published>2024-05-10T14:22:55Z</published>
    <updated>2024-05-10T14:26:32Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/dei-is-done-minus-the-mop-up-b3bbbb64"/>
    <title>DEI is done (minus the mop up)</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;In November of 2022, I wrote about &lt;a href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/the-waning-days-of-dei-s-dominance-9a5b656c"&gt;the waning days of DEI's dominance&lt;/a&gt;, and enumerated four factors that I saw as primary drivers of this decline. Those waning days have now been brought to a close, and DEI, as an obsessive, ideological preoccupation of the corporate world, is done. Witness this tabulation of DEI (and ESG) mentions in earnings reports, &lt;a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/woke-capitalism-reversal-google-unilever-bud-light-esg-dei-2024-5"&gt;reported by Business Insider&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;  &lt;figure class="attachment attachment--preview attachment--lightboxable attachment--png"&gt;
      &lt;a download="dei-esg-mentions.png" title="Download dei-esg-mentions.png" data-click-proxy-target="lightbox_link_blob_1652910038" href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/b3bbbb64/blobs/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaHNLd2ZXWjRWaSIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoiYmxvYl9pZCJ9fQ==--a76ac4873e40bd459b37b59bc79ec660d16d46c9/dei-esg-mentions.png?disposition=attachment"&gt;
        &lt;img src="https://world.hey.com/dhh/b3bbbb64/representations/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaHNLd2ZXWjRWaSIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoiYmxvYl9pZCJ9fQ==--a76ac4873e40bd459b37b59bc79ec660d16d46c9/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaDdDam9MWm05eWJXRjBTU0lJY0c1bkJqb0dSVlE2RkhKbGMybDZaVjkwYjE5c2FXMXBkRnNIYVFLQUIya0NBQVU2REhGMVlXeHBkSGxwU3pvTGJHOWhaR1Z5ZXdZNkNYQmhaMlV3T2cxamIyRnNaWE5qWlZRPSIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoidmFyaWF0aW9uIn19--946116ea0c454412635aa7309bd9472bf633014c/dei-esg-mentions.png" alt="dei-esg-mentions.png" srcset="https://world.hey.com/dhh/b3bbbb64/representations/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaHNLd2ZXWjRWaSIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoiYmxvYl9pZCJ9fQ==--a76ac4873e40bd459b37b59bc79ec660d16d46c9/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaDdDam9MWm05eWJXRjBTU0lJY0c1bkJqb0dSVlE2RkhKbGMybDZaVjkwYjE5c2FXMXBkRnNIYVFJQUQya0NBQW82REhGMVlXeHBkSGxwUVRvTGJHOWhaR1Z5ZXdZNkNYQmhaMlV3T2cxamIyRnNaWE5qWlZRPSIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoidmFyaWF0aW9uIn19--8c0bbbd8bfe72a73b222ec1c20265f8631973dc9/dei-esg-mentions.png 2x, https://world.hey.com/dhh/b3bbbb64/representations/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaHNLd2ZXWjRWaSIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoiYmxvYl9pZCJ9fQ==--a76ac4873e40bd459b37b59bc79ec660d16d46c9/eyJfcmFpbHMiOnsibWVzc2FnZSI6IkJBaDdDam9MWm05eWJXRjBTU0lJY0c1bkJqb0dSVlE2RkhKbGMybDZaVjkwYjE5c2FXMXBkRnNIYVFLQUZta0NBQTg2REhGMVlXeHBkSGxwUERvTGJHOWhaR1Z5ZXdZNkNYQmhaMlV3T2cxamIyRnNaWE5qWlZRPSIsImV4cCI6bnVsbCwicHVyIjoidmFyaWF0aW9uIn19--d2fed6b5089e475a3013538949ec7f311ac6e345/dei-esg-mentions.png 3x" decoding="async" loading="lazy"&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;
  &lt;/figure&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's over. And thank heavens for that! This graph perfectly captures the temporary insanity of what those nutty years were really like in corporate America. An explosion of sanctimony, triggered by the fallacy that racial disparities in the office (and elsewhere) could only be explained by systemic racism. And, worse still, that the way to counteract this mirage was by compensatory discrimination against &amp;quot;model minorities&amp;quot; (&lt;a href="https://nymag.com/intelligencer/2022/02/the-left-is-gaslighting-asian-americans-on-school-admissions.html"&gt;mostly Asians&lt;/a&gt;) and &amp;quot;whiteness&amp;quot;, as prescribed by &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/quotes/9980984-the-defining-question-is-whether-the-discrimination-is-creating-equity"&gt;the dogma of Antiracism&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;And with this explosion of sanctimony came a brief but suffocating culture of intimidation. Anyone who dared question the theology of high priests of this new religion, like DiAngelo or Kendi, were hounded and frequently banished by ideological thugs. &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;It didn't matter if the hounded were low-level employees who hadn't kept up with latest woke dictionary (is it latinx now? or latine? &lt;a href="https://hispanicexecutive.com/latinx-latine-explainer/"&gt;or?&lt;/a&gt;), executives who dared to claim that meritocracy might actually be a good thing, or comedians making jokes about the insufferable fake piety of it all. There were pitchforks enough to chase all transgressors, big or small.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;But now it's done. The tide has turned. The People are sick of this shit. So that's it. All there's left to do is mop up, then make sure we harden our defenses for the next time agitating embers come flying.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>David Heinemeier Hansson</name>
      <email>dhh@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/36998</id>
    <published>2024-05-09T00:34:49Z</published>
    <updated>2024-05-09T00:34:49Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/hating-apple-goes-mainstream-fe740007"/>
    <title>Hating Apple goes mainstream</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;This isn't just about one awful ad. I mean, yes, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/tim_cook/status/1787864325258162239"&gt;the ad truly is awful&lt;/a&gt;. It symbolizes everything everyone has ever hated about digitization. It celebrates a lossy, creative compression for the most flimsy reason: An iPad shedding an irrelevant millimeter or two. It's destruction of beloved musical instruments is the perfect metaphor for how utterly tone-deaf technologists are capable of being. But the real story is just how little saved up goodwill Apple had in the bank to compensate for the outrage.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;That's because Apple has lost its presumption of good faith over the last five years with an ever-larger group of people, and now we've reached a tipping point. A year ago, I'm sure this awful ad would have gotten push back, but I'm also sure we'd heard more &amp;quot;it's not that big of a deal&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;what Apple really meant to say was...&amp;quot; from the stalwart Apple apologists the company has been able to count on for decades. But it's awfully quiet on the fan-boy front.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;This should all be eerily familiar to anyone who saw Microsoft fall from grace in the 90s. From being America's favorite software company to being the bully pursued by the DOJ for illegalities. Just like Apple now, Microsoft's reputation and good standing suddenly evaporated seemingly overnight once enough critical stories had accumulated about its behavior.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's not easy to predict these tipping points. Tim Cook enthusiastically introduced this awful ad with a big smile, and I'm sure he's sitting with at least some sense of &amp;quot;wtf just happened?&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;why don't they love us any more?&amp;quot;. Because companies like Apple almost have to ignore the haters as the cost of doing business, but then they also can't easily tell when the sentiment has changed from &amp;quot;the usual number&amp;quot; to &amp;quot;one too many&amp;quot;. And then, boom, the game is forever changed.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;I think this is bound to come as a bigger surprise to Apple than it would have almost any other company. Apple had such treasure chest of goodwill from decades as first an underdog, then unchallenged innovator. But today they're a near three-trillion dollar company, battling sovereigns on both sides of the Atlantic, putting out mostly incremental updates to mature products. Nobody is lining up with a tent to buy a new iPhone any more. The Vision Pro had at best a mediocre launch. Oh, and now the company is even the creator of cringy ads, introduced by a cringy CEO.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;Not that this is a mortal wound or even a story anyone is likely to remember in a month. But it is an early indicator that Apple's run on easy street is over. And that's going to require a new approach, which Apple probably won't embrace until they've embarrassed themselves a few more times (like they did with &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QNv9PRDIhes"&gt;another cringe ad&lt;/a&gt; from a little while back).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Everything is great until it isn't.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>David Heinemeier Hansson</name>
      <email>dhh@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/36971</id>
    <published>2024-05-07T17:41:08Z</published>
    <updated>2024-05-07T17:41:08Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/the-last-railsconf-c6188593"/>
    <title>The last RailsConf</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;Few numbers exemplified the early growth of Rails like attendance at RailsConf. I think we started with something like 400-600 attendees at the inaugural conference in Chicago in 2006, then just kept doubling year over year, as Rails went to the moon. If memory serves me right, we had something like 1,800 attendees in 2008? It was rapid, it was wild, but next year, it'll be over. &lt;a href="https://rubycentral.org/news/anewearforrubycentralevents/"&gt;RailsConf 2025 will be the last RailsConf&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;This is for the best. RailsConf, as it exists today, is a legacy from when the Rails ecosystem didn't have its own guardian institution. For many years, it was left to Ruby Central to fill this role, but that was always going to be a secondary pursuit to their primary mission of furthering Ruby in general. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;But now we have &lt;a href="https://rubyonrails.org/foundation"&gt;The Rails Foundation&lt;/a&gt;, which is focused 100% on Rails, backed by the biggest names in ecosystem. It's also the organizer of &lt;a href="https://rubyonrails.org/world/"&gt;Rails World&lt;/a&gt;, which just sold out its own thousand-attendee conference in Toronto this coming September -- &lt;a href="https://x.com/dhh/status/1785368652440916121"&gt;in less than twenty minutes&lt;/a&gt;! The baton has been passed.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;This is good. With Ruby Central focusing their efforts on general-purpose Ruby endeavors, like maintaining Bundler and RubyGems, as well as putting on &lt;a href="https://rubyconf.org/"&gt;RubyConf&lt;/a&gt;, the division of responsibilities between it and The Rails Foundation is now clear. Which makes it much easier for both organizations to collaborate on furthering Ruby on Rails, each putting emphasis on their side of the conjunction.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;I'm going to choose to remember RailsConf for all the wonderful memories it brought me and the ecosystem, especially in the early years. Working with the original crew of Chad Fowler, David A. Black, and Rich Kilmer was the treat of a lifetime. We bootstrapped something from nothing, turned it into an epoch-defining event, and I delivered some of &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GFhoSMD6idk"&gt;my&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9LfmrkyP81M"&gt;most&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4PVViBjukAE"&gt;memorable&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=zKyv-IGvgGE"&gt;keynotes&lt;/a&gt; in that era.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;It's a bit of a shame &lt;a href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/no-railsconf-faa7935e"&gt;what happened later&lt;/a&gt;, during those mad years in and immediately following the pandemic, but that kind of nonsense is thankfully now largely behind us, not just in the Ruby world, but in tech in general. And Ruby Central is now almost entirely run by people who didn't have anything to do with that debacle anyway. Making it much easier just to look forward, and simply appreciate that those odd years helped motivate finally getting The Rails Foundation off the ground.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Either way, the future of Rails shines incredibly bright. The ideal of &lt;a href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/the-one-person-framework-711e6318"&gt;the one-person framework&lt;/a&gt; has never been more relevant. The world has woken up from the ZIRP years with &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iqXjGiQ_D-A&amp;amp;t=725s"&gt;a complexity hang-over&lt;/a&gt;, and Rails is the perfect painkiller. From &lt;a href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/once-1-is-entirely-nobuild-for-the-front-end-ce56f6d7"&gt;#nobuild&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href="https://kamal-deploy.org/"&gt;bare-metal deployment&lt;/a&gt; to the eternal appeal of a full-stack solution comprised by Active Record, Action Pack, Active Support, and the million other arguments and assets that underpin the modern appeal of Rails. We never went away, but the renaissance is palpable none the less.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;So I raise my glass to the final RailsConf. Let's go out with a bang in 2025, celebrate the legacy, and then keep plucking away on spreading the joy of beautiful code, incredible productivity, and programmer-centric development with Ruby on Rails. Cheers!&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>David Heinemeier Hansson</name>
      <email>dhh@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/36801</id>
    <published>2024-04-30T15:32:01Z</published>
    <updated>2024-05-13T18:54:59Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/magic-machines-10c534bd"/>
    <title>Magic machines</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;There's an interesting psychological phenomenon where programmers tend to ascribe more trust to computers run by anyone but themselves. Perhaps it's a corollary to imposter syndrome, which leads programmers to believe that if a computer is operated by AWS or SaaS or literally anyone else, it must be more secure, better managed, less buggy, and ultimately purer. I wish that was so, but there are no magic machines and no magic operators. Just the same kind of potentially faulty bits and brains.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;A great example of this was the feedback to our declaration that &lt;a href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/we-re-moving-continuous-integration-back-to-developer-machines-3ac6c611"&gt;we're bringing continuous integration back to developer machines&lt;/a&gt;. The most common objection was to invoke &amp;quot;it works on my machine&amp;quot;, as to imply that developer machines were somehow a different breed than the ones running in the cloud or the data center. They really aren't! The computer running tests remotely is indeed just that: Another computer. It isn't magical, and it's no less prone to be reliant on unaccounted for dependencies or environmental factors.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;In fact, when it comes to testing, it's a feature not a bug to have the suite run on multiple machines. It's like an extra fuzzy check that will uncover undeclared dependencies, and help you produce a more resilient system. Because even the best CI setup isn't production. And just because it works in CI doesn't mean it'll be free of issues in production.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;Which leads us to the whole point of testing systems in the first place: It's about confidence, not certainty. The road to programmer misery is paved with delusional aspirations that you can ever be fully, truly certain that any sufficiently complicated system will ever work as intended in production. All you have is degrees of confidence to trade-off against increasingly cumbersome protocols and procedures. There's no such thing as 100% test coverage that's meaningful and achievable at the same time.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;And it's the fundamental lack of confidence in their own abilities that lead programmers to think that the people operating their cloud computers are so much smarter or better than they are. They rarely are. They're just hidden, and it's that opaqueness that false implies a higher competence. If only you knew what kind of frazzled mechanical turk it takes to run most cloud institutions or SaaS operations, you wouldn't be so quick to doubt your own abilities.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;There's no magic class of computers and no magic class of computing clerics. &amp;quot;It works on my computer&amp;quot; is just the midwit version of &amp;quot;it works on THAT computer&amp;quot;. It's all just computers. You can figure them out, you can make them dance.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>David Heinemeier Hansson</name>
      <email>dhh@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/36775</id>
    <published>2024-04-29T18:40:53Z</published>
    <updated>2024-04-29T18:40:53Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/we-re-moving-continuous-integration-back-to-developer-machines-3ac6c611"/>
    <title>We're moving continuous integration back to developer machines</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;Between running Rubocop style rules, Brakeman security scans, and model-controller-system tests, it takes our remote BuildKite-based continuous integration setup about 5m30s to verify a code change is ready to ship for HEY. My Intel 14900K-based Linux box can do that in less than half the time (and my M3 Max isn't that much slower!). So we're going to drop the remote runners and just bring continuous integration back to developer machines at 37signals.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;It's remarkable how big of a leap multi-core developer machines have taken over the last five-to-seven years or so. Running all these checks and validations in a reasonable time on a local machine would have been unthinkable not too long ago. But the 14900K has over 20 cores, the M3 Max has 16, and even a lowly M2 MacBook has 8. They're all capable of doing a tremendous amount of parallelized work that would have seem fantastical to do locally in the mid 2010s.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;HEY is a pretty substantial code base too. About 55,000 lines of Ruby code, which is verified by some 5,000 test cases along with another 300-some system tests. Virtually all of these tests go through the full-stack and hit the database. These are not mocked to the hilt.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;To me, the most satisfying part of the improved performance of modern developer CPUs is the possibility to simplify our stacks. Installing, operating, and caring for a remote CI setup is a substantial complication. Either you do it on your own hardware, and deal with that complexity directly, or you pay through the nose for a cloud-based setup. Getting to flush all of it down the simplification drain is an amazing step forward.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;In fact, it's what I like most about paying attention to the progress of our platforms. Oh, browsers now have really good JavaScript and CSS engines? Awesome. &lt;a href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/once-1-is-entirely-nobuild-for-the-front-end-ce56f6d7"&gt;Let's go #nobuild&lt;/a&gt;. Oh, developer CPUs now have dozens of cores? Sweet. &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/dhh/c5051aae633ff91bc4ce30528e4f0b60"&gt;Let's pull CI home&lt;/a&gt;. Oh, single-core performance is way up? Wonderful. &lt;a href="https://x.com/dhh/status/1783291561402577279"&gt;Let's drop gotcha-hinged accelerators like Spring&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;As always, the simplified future is not evenly distributed. I can't see the likes of Shopify or GitHub being able to run the full battery of tests against their millions of lines of code locally any time soon. But 99.99% of all web apps are much closer to HEY in breadth than they are to those behemoths. And small teams ought to remove all the moving parts possible. Never aspire to a more complicated stack than what your application calls for.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;So we need to keep burning those &lt;a href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/introducing-propshaft-ee60f4f6"&gt;bridges of complexity&lt;/a&gt; once we get to the other side. I can't wait to set fire to every single one of the remote continuous integration bridges we have here at 37signals. Progress is a bonfire.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>David Heinemeier Hansson</name>
      <email>dhh@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/36720</id>
    <published>2024-04-26T18:54:39Z</published>
    <updated>2024-04-26T20:36:13Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/i-could-have-been-happy-with-windows-bd4a7d01"/>
    <title>I could have been happy with Windows</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;After more than twenty years on the mac, it was always going to be difficult for me to leave Apple. I've simply not been in the market for another computing platform in decades. Sure, I've &lt;a href="https://signalvnoise.com/svn3/back-to-windows-after-twenty-years/"&gt;dabbled a bit&lt;/a&gt; here and there, but never with true commitment. It wasn't until &lt;a href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/apple-is-in-its-ballmer-era-339b0713"&gt;Cupertino broke my camel's back&lt;/a&gt; this year that I suddenly had the motivation needed to uproot everything. And when I did, I learned that Windows has turned into a wonderful web developer's platform thanks to the Windows Subsystem for Linux (WSL).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;I'm not going to lie and say I loved everything about Windows. But after &lt;a href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/fonts-don-t-have-to-look-awful-on-windows-564c9d2f"&gt;the question of font rendering was settled&lt;/a&gt;, and I came to terms with &lt;a href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/finding-the-last-editor-dae701cc"&gt;giving up TextMate&lt;/a&gt;, it felt perfectly adequate. Better than adequate, actually. It felt nice. Nice knowing that there was a real, realistic, and compelling alternative to the mac, and that most of my aversion to Windows was based on outdated facts or misconceptions.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;So I &lt;a href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/committing-to-windows-2d6388fd"&gt;made the commitment&lt;/a&gt;. Only to &lt;a href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/imperfections-create-connections-bc87d630"&gt;fall in love with a quirky piece of hardware&lt;/a&gt; from a small company called Framework shortly thereafter. That in turn lead to taking another look at running Linux outright, as the AMD chip inside the Framework simply &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/dhh/status/1769207569690829147"&gt;punched harder&lt;/a&gt; with the penguin in charge.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;This coincided with a month-long trip away from home where all I brought was the Framework 13 running Ubuntu. And that taught me two things: Most of &lt;a href="https://x.com/cmuratori/status/1783274430376120770"&gt;the jokes&lt;/a&gt; about Linux are true! There are more rabbit holes, more gotchas, and less polish. But I also learned, and this was the real surprise, that I scarcely minded at all! That in fact running Linux, and running into many of the little issues that often entails, was a surprisingly delightful and educational experience.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;As an example, I've been trying for a while to get my desktop PC, which has an Nvidia 4090 GPU, to work with my Apple XDR 6K monitor, which only accepts Thunderbolt 3. This involved sourcing &lt;a href="https://www.ebay.com/itm/334853973344?var=544017268128"&gt;an exotic Huawei DisplayPort + 2 USB-A =&amp;gt; USB C cable&lt;/a&gt;. Then learning everything about monitor EDIDs, xorg.conf, kernel parameters, Nvidia driver versions, and about a million other topics that are very close to the metal and very far from the Apple experience (and &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/dhh/status/1782853870886203791"&gt;I still haven't cracked the nut!&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;But rather than being frustrated with things not just working out of the box, I embraced the adventure. There's a certain nostalgia here, I'm sure. I grew up with computers that needed far more tender, love, and care to work well. Where IRQ conflicts had to be resolved before the SoundBlaster card would work for Wing Commander. Computers required some assembly, and &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/IKEA_effect"&gt;as IKEA knows&lt;/a&gt;, it made us love them more. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;So here I am. I still have Windows available as a dual-boot option on the desktop, but the Framework 13 has been running Ubuntu exclusively the whole time, it's my daily driver at the moment, and now that I've acclimated, Linux just feels right. I love the Tactile windows manager for Gnome. I've figured out how to easily fill out my PDFs using Xournal++. Typora is giving me that iA Writer-like distraction-free typing experience I've come to love. And, for now, I've come to terms with VSCode. (See &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/dhh/159b129f511f76db3ae8adb463f70d05"&gt;my current setup script&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;Would I recommend this expedition to everyone? No. I think if the idea of having to occasionally tinker with kernel parameters or display drivers give you nightmares, you probably shouldn't run Linux on your primary computer. But I'd also say that it's hard to know whether you'll find some zen of motorcycle maintenance in knowing how to tighten the timing chain of Ubuntu before you try. Especially if you've been cocooned inside the Apple bubble forever.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;For a lot of people, Windows is probably the better alternative to the mac. And that's great! We ought to have AT LEAST three good options for personal computing in the modern age, and now I've come to realize that we do.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;I'm just happy this exodus happened. I learned something new about myself. I tried a million combinations. And I discovered a real affinity for Framework and Ubuntu. I'd invite you to give it a go, if you're in the mood for a trek. Do it not because it is easy, but because it is hard. See what kind of computing stuff you're made of. Oh, and have fun!&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>David Heinemeier Hansson</name>
      <email>dhh@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/36699</id>
    <published>2024-04-25T22:15:23Z</published>
    <updated>2024-04-25T22:15:23Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/the-gift-of-ambition-e7b41ffc"/>
    <title>The gift of ambition</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;The Babylon Bee ran &lt;a href="https://babylonbee.com/news/study-finds-100-of-men-would-immediately-leave-their-desk-job-if-asked-to-embark-upon-a-trans-antarctic-expedition-on-a-big-wooden-ship"&gt;this amazing bit&lt;/a&gt; last year: &amp;quot;Study Finds 100% Of Men Would Immediately Leave Their Desk Job If Asked To Embark Upon A Trans-Antarctic Expedition On A Big Wooden Ship&amp;quot;. Yes. Exactly. Modern office workers are often starved for ambition, adventure, and even discomfort. This is why there's an endless line of recruits willing to sign up to work for leaders like Musk, despite his reputation for being an erratic hard ass. The ambition is worth it. Because real ambition is rare.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;It's the lack of ambition that fuels the malaise of a bullshit job. Work so aspirationally underwhelming that it's possible to coast and imagine how the world wouldn't be an iota different if the work wasn't done. A perfect recipe for existential dread and despair.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;But while the stereotype of ambition is indeed someone like Elon Musk (or Steve Jobs, before that), I don't think you literally need to aim for Mars to stir the heart of sailors. Nor do I think you need to be as abrasive or demanding, as the stereotype implies. That's the balance we've been trying to find at 37signals since its inception: The vision of a calm company compatible with ambition.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's not always easy. If you talk for long enough about the fact that &lt;a href="https://37signals.com/podcast/8s-enough-40s-plenty/"&gt;40 hours a week ought to be enough&lt;/a&gt;, that vacations should be free of homing beacons, and how it literally &lt;a href="https://basecamp.com/books/calm"&gt;doesn't have to be crazy at work&lt;/a&gt;, people inside and out your company might soon think that's indeed all there is. That the ultimate goal of the company is to provide a cush and coasting existence. But that's not why I get out of bed in the morning.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;The aspiration of a calm company is to me exactly the opposite. To prove how much faster and further you can go if you &lt;a href="https://basecamp.com/gettingreal/03.4-embrace-constraints"&gt;embrace constraints&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://signalvnoise.com/svn3/small-is-not-a-stepping-stone/"&gt;stay small&lt;/a&gt;, and trust skilled professionals to &lt;a href="https://basecamp.com/justletmedomyjob"&gt;get the job done&lt;/a&gt;. That is, the calm company is a method for getting where we really want to go. It's not a destination in and of itself.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;In fact, I'd rather work in place where it was crazy all the time, if we're trying to get somewhere, than I'd work somewhere perfectly calm that's just spinning the wheels. But the point is that I don't think these objectives are in opposition. Being ambitious and calm is like being smooth and fast. Big, erratic, dramatic movements might feel like they're getting you somewhere, but the stop watch usually reveals the opposite.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;But what is ambition, exactly? To me, it's a leap of faith. A belief in the possibility of success without all the evidence to justify it a priori. A trust that whatever challenges we'll face between here and there, we'll be able to figure them out. It's a confidence in the strength of human ingenuity. And a bet that it takes a goal just beyond the reach of the plausible to get the best out of us all.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;That ambition can be applied to all aspects of a project. The timeline, the people, the problem, the tech. To tickle our sense of adventure, some of it has to be daring and bold. Maybe it's not enough people, not enough time, new tech, novel problems. Whatever it is, there must be an x factor, an unknown. If we can quantify it all before we even begin, the ambition disappears.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;And in that lack of certainly lies the discomfort, lies the leap. Betting on your ability to figure it out means taking a risk. Maybe you won't figure it out! Maybe we really didn't have enough people! Maybe we'll fail. But it's exactly the possibility of failure that gives the effort its meaning and its value.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;In the lore of Steve Jobs, you'll find plenty of anecdotes from people who really didn't care for how he treated them or their colleagues at times, but who still credit the projects they worked on for him at Apple as the most meaningful ones of their career. I'm sure the same is true with Musk. These encapsulate the paradox that, psychologically speaking, I don't think most people know what makes them fulfilled at work. (But it isn't the ping pong or the free massage.)&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Without a dash of the unpredictable, we all wither away. The chase for security and surety only works as a thrill if you never truly get there. Our competency only grows when we stretch it slightly beyond its breaking point from time to time.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;So keep calm, yes, but for all that is holy, carry on by being ambitious.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>David Heinemeier Hansson</name>
      <email>dhh@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/36695</id>
    <published>2024-04-25T17:20:52Z</published>
    <updated>2024-04-25T17:20:52Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/villains-may-live-long-enough-to-become-heroes-6405ae8c"/>
    <title>Villains may live long enough to become heroes</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;The first tech company I ever really despised was Microsoft. This was back in the 1990s, the era of &lt;a href="https://www.deseret.com/1999/1/23/19425051/microsoft-executive-denies-threat-to-cut-off-air-supply/"&gt;&amp;quot;cutting off the air supply&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt;, of &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Embrace,_extend,_and_extinguish"&gt;embrace-extend-extinguish&lt;/a&gt;, of &lt;a href="https://www.theregister.com/2001/06/02/ballmer_linux_is_a_cancer/"&gt;open source as a &amp;quot;cancer&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt;, and of Bill Gates before he sought reputational refugee in philanthropy. What made the animosity so strong was the sense of being trapped. That the alternatives to the Wintel monopoly of the time was so inferior as to essentially require giving up on modern computing.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;So when Apple released the first Unix-powered OSX machines at the turn of the millennium, I felt relieved. Saved, even. Finally -- FINALLY!! -- a real choice. Apple provided an escape hatch for computing without giving up on modernity, and I came to love them for it.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;But that was then and this is now. Microsoft has completed an astounding redemption arc since. They've gone from being the sworn enemy of open source to one of the biggest sponsors of it. They've been exemplary stewards of GitHub. They've won the hearts and minds of developers with VSCode &lt;a href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/vscode-wsl-makes-windows-awesome-for-web-development-9bc4d528"&gt;fair and square&lt;/a&gt;. They've even put Linux inside of Windows with WSL! In short, they've gone from being a villain to a hero in a wide array of domains. Open source most of all. And I love it. They deserve all the accolades.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Meanwhile, Apple... Well, I've talked enough about Apple. So let's talk about something new: Meta.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;I can't say I ever despised Meta, then Facebook, quite like I did Microsoft. But I sure as shit wasn't a fan. And I remain a staunch opponent of targeted advertising, the privacy assault that inevitably comes with them, and what it's done to the web. But I've come to appreciate that there are bigger challenges facing us than invasive ads. Much bigger.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;Take AI. Zuckerberg's embrace of open source AI, now making headlines with &lt;a href="https://ai.meta.com/blog/meta-llama-3/"&gt;the public release of Llama 3&lt;/a&gt;, is an invaluable counter to the cartel-adjacent bullshit of &amp;quot;AI safety &amp;amp; ethics&amp;quot; that would see the likes of OpenAI and Google &lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2023/05/16/technology/openai-altman-artificial-intelligence-regulation.html"&gt;conspire with governments&lt;/a&gt; around the world to determine what math should be allowed to predict the next token. I've seen this movie before, and I'm not interested in a rerun.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;In fact, Facebook itself was one of the main characters in the previous show. The still going battle over misinformation/disinformation/malinformation, which continues to see the awful fusion of state and platforms through censors and algorithms in controlling The Narrative. Whatever trust I may once have had in objective third-party &amp;quot;fact checkers&amp;quot; have long since evaporated from &lt;a href="https://www.tabletmag.com/sections/news/articles/invasion-fact-checkers"&gt;the catastrophic track record&lt;/a&gt; of these &lt;a href="https://nypost.com/2021/12/14/facebook-admits-the-truth-fact-checks-are-really-just-lefty-opinion/"&gt;anything-but-neutral&lt;/a&gt;, would-be arbiters of truth.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;I don't pretend that either of these problems are easy or even that they have solutions. But they certainly have different potential outcomes and trade-offs. Some worse than others. And the prospect of having AI exclusively fine-tuned by the likes of &lt;a href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/google-s-sad-ideological-capture-was-exactly-what-we-were-trying-to-avoid-67fad361"&gt;whoever did Gemini&lt;/a&gt; or directed by bureaucrats trying to &amp;quot;save democracy&amp;quot; by banning the opposition, yeah, no thanks. I'll take my chances with the unadulterated math or speech any day.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Which makes Zuckerberg's transformation so important. I think a lot of the naivete he had, as did many, about the role of content moderation, truth arbiters, and platform control has been replaced by high degrees of skepticism. And I certainly think that after being &lt;a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/kateoflahertyuk/2022/04/23/apple-just-issued-stunning-12-billion-blow-to-facebook/?sh=304c25119074"&gt;humiliated by Apple via ATT&lt;/a&gt;, he's as motivated as anyone to prevent the next frontier of computing to be dominated by anyone (if it can't be himself!).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;This is good. And it's not good because I have some special insight into Zuckerberg's &amp;quot;heart of hearts&amp;quot;. I'm sure his dedication to open source AI is as motivated by self-interest as anyone in that position ever was. That's not a bug! It's a feature! Adam Smith saw it clearly in Wealth of Nations from 1776:&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;It is not from the benevolence of the butcher, the brewer, or the baker, that we expect our dinner, but from their regard to their own interest. We address ourselves, not to their humanity but to their self-love, and never talk to them of our own necessities but of their advantages.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;We don't need altruism to save us, we need incentives. We need competition. We need free markets for products, platforms, services, ideas, speech, and AI. We need to put the locus of control with consumers and individuals, not bureaucrats and monopolists.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;That's always going to be the struggle. Whenever we achieve anything close to its ideal, like the marvel of the worldwide web, it constantly has to be guarded against regression. So if Microsoft proves to be aligned with some of those causes some of the time, I shall cheer them on, and I shall quell my quarreling. And if Meta does the same, they too shall receive my praise. (Or so I imagine Smith would sound!).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;We badly need more powerful champions and heroes of free markets and free thought. Enough that I'm more than willing to commute the sentencing of former villains who've served their time and changed their minds. And enough that I'm comfortable stack ranking my concerns about society, and realizing that targeted ads just aren't as important as the freedoms defined above.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;Let's go, Zuck. Give 'em hell.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>David Heinemeier Hansson</name>
      <email>dhh@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/36653</id>
    <published>2024-04-23T16:55:51Z</published>
    <updated>2024-04-23T16:55:51Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/as-we-forgive-those-who-trespass-against-us-c5979c81"/>
    <title>As we forgive those who trespass against us</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;Google's announcement that they're &lt;a href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/we-are-a-place-of-business-a451eddf"&gt;done discussing politics at work&lt;/a&gt; widely echoed the policy changes Coinbase and we at 37signals did a few years back. So yesterday, I did two separate interviews with media outlets on the topic. And we spoke in part about those early weeks of reaction to our changes, as Twitter went crazy in response to the story. What was it like to briefly be the main, hated characters on the internet?&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;In the moment, it was awful, but in retrospect, it was a gift. &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;A gift as a mirror, causing me to reflect on how I might have been part of a similar mob, on other topics, in different ways. A gift of a &lt;a href="https://www.depthnotwidth.com/the-misogi-challenge-taking-risks-and-crushing-your-comfort-zone/"&gt;misogi challenge&lt;/a&gt; of character, bringing the satisfaction of overcoming a vicious social purgatory. But above all, the gift of knowing who was there for me and who wasn't.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;It's a cliché, but &amp;quot;knowing who your friends are&amp;quot; really is a blessing. We walk through life much of the time without really knowing who'll be there when the going gets tough -- and our guesses are often wrong. Only the moment of truth, a real crisis, can clarify who's who and what's what. And so it did for me.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;It brought unexpected friends and allies out in the light, and it revealed which friends and acquaintances would rather crawl back in the woodwork than stand by my side. I was surprised on both sides.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;But while I'll never forget who made what choice, I've committed myself to forgive those who trespassed against me. In &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/shorts/rx5i_HztXxQ"&gt;that Mike Tyson'esque way&lt;/a&gt; of refusing to let any of them change me. I'm certain I've been the weak link in past situations from time to time. I'm certain I've been too lazy or too timid to reach out to support someone who I knew needed it. I don't have many regrets in life, but the ones I have usually fall into this category: I should have been there for someone.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;Beyond the personal, I think forgiving our trespassers is how we get out of this specific mess. The period from the late 2010s until at least 2022 really was crazy. It swept up so many otherwise kind and caring people into an ideology predicated on dividing us all into oppressors/oppressed, privileged/not, and other false dichotomies and identities. The way out of bad ideas like that is not a vendetta, but forgiveness. We all have the capacity for being swept up in a social movement or mob. But equally, we all have the path of finding our way out again.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;I think there are a lot of people sitting right now with a nagging sense of regret from what they partook in during that crazy era. Who tried on the cape of being a Social Justice Warrior, but ultimately found it suffocating both intellectually and culturally. That's the reckoning we're going through right now.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;The worst thing we can do to slow down the rejection of these bad ideas is by forever tarring people who were momentarily taken in by them. Yes, we should absolutely have a vigorous inquiry into the nature of these bad ideas, trace their lineage, and uncover their tragedies. But we can't persecute every individual who in a moment of fear, weakness or ignorance signed on to carry a torch because that's what everyone else was doing at the time.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;That is to say, it's more important that we expedite and complete the broad societal rejection of bad ideas than it is to pursue every bad actor until the end of the earth. That's exactly why this vicious ideology proved so unstable, and unable to retain the peak of its power. It kept eating its own for ever-smaller transgressions against an ever-shifting doctrine. To beat that nonsense back, the side of sanity has to do the opposite. Be broader, more forgiving, and less high strung.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;Lead us not into temptation of retaliation.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>David Heinemeier Hansson</name>
      <email>dhh@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/36589</id>
    <published>2024-04-19T12:30:50Z</published>
    <updated>2024-04-19T13:58:02Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/we-are-a-place-of-business-a451eddf"/>
    <title>We are a place of business</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;After the &lt;a href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/google-s-sad-ideological-capture-was-exactly-what-we-were-trying-to-avoid-67fad361"&gt;disastrous launch of their Gemini AI&lt;/a&gt;, which insisted that George Washington was actually Black and couldn't decide whether Musk's tweets or Hitler was worse, Google's response was timid and weak. This was just a bug! A problem with QA! It absolutely, positively wasn't a reflection of corrupted culture at Google, which now appeared to put ideology over accuracy. Really, really!&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Anyone watching that shit show would be right to wonder whether one of America's great technology companies had fallen completely into the hands of &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Woke-Racism-Religion-Betrayed-America-ebook/dp/B095JLK96B/"&gt;the new theocracy&lt;/a&gt;. I certainly did. &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;But now comes evidence that Google perhaps isn't totally lost, even if an internal war over its origin principles is very much raging. One pitting the mission of organizing the world's information and making it useful against the newspeak Trust &amp;amp; Safety goal of controlling narratives and countering &lt;a href="https://reason.com/2023/03/22/the-crusade-against-malinformation-explicitly-targets-inconvenient-truths/"&gt;malinformation&lt;/a&gt; (i.e. inconvenient truths).&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;This played out in stereotype as 28 Googlers occupied the CEO of Google Cloud's office for 10 hours this week, defaced property, and prevented other Googlers from doing their work. Because Google provides cloud services to Israel, said the occupiers. And thus The Current Thing demanded it be stopped by whatever means possible. (Remember when The Current Thing was that GitHub shouldn't offer its technology to ICE because &amp;quot;kids in cages&amp;quot;? Same thing).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;But then the most amazing thing happened. There was no drawn-out investigation. No saccharine statements about employee's rights to occupy offices, preventing work from happening, or advance their political agenda at work. Nope. &lt;a href="https://nypost.com/2024/04/17/business/google-fires-28-employees-involved-in-sit-in-protest-over-1-2b-israel-contract/"&gt;They were just fired&lt;/a&gt;. Immediately. All 28 of them.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Bravo.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;Google's bottom line? &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/yashar/status/1780802630509613091"&gt;&amp;quot;This is a place of business&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt;. And while employees have the lawful right to protest their working conditions, they do not have the right to prevent a business from carrying out its normal course of commerce over a disagreement in politics. So that was that.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;But it gets better. Google followed up the unceremonious firings by calling an end to employees bringing their politics to the office. Just &lt;a href="https://www.coinbase.com/blog/coinbase-is-a-mission-focused-company"&gt;like Coinbase did&lt;/a&gt;, just &lt;a href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/basecamp-s-new-etiquette-regarding-societal-politics-at-work-b44bef69"&gt;like we did&lt;/a&gt;. The language was &lt;a href="https://blog.google/inside-google/company-announcements/building-ai-future-april-2024/"&gt;spot on&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;quot;But ultimately we are a workplace and our policies and expectations are clear: this is a business, and not a place to act in a way that disrupts coworkers or makes them feel unsafe, to attempt to use the company as a personal platform, or to fight over disruptive issues or debate politics. This is too important a moment as a company for us to be distracted.&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;Three years ago, taking a common-sense position like this would have been met with drama and outage in the media and on Twitter. Today I doubt it'll bring more than a ripple outside of a few activist echo chambers on Mastodon. Amazing progress!&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Note, none of this pertains to what you think about &lt;a href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/the-current-villain-63710982"&gt;The Current Thing&lt;/a&gt; that provided the trigger this time. It could just as well had been BLM, Russiagate, climate change, or a million other hot-button topics that have occupied the role as The Current Thing, and been used to justify these kinds of insufferable activists yelling at their boss.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;We've not just &lt;a href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/proof-of-the-peak-ede4199c"&gt;passed the peak of the nonsense&lt;/a&gt; that nearly swallowed corporate America whole, but we're now seeing them repudiate it head on. If Google, with it's employment roster still packed with people sympathetic to the new theocracy, can put its foot down, so can the rest of the Fortune 500 and beyond. It's time they all say: &amp;quot;This is a place of business&amp;quot;.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>David Heinemeier Hansson</name>
      <email>dhh@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/36518</id>
    <published>2024-04-15T13:46:50Z</published>
    <updated>2024-04-21T04:13:26Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/forcing-master-to-main-was-a-good-faith-exploit-b21ee30c"/>
    <title>Forcing master to main was a good faith exploit</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;I never actually cared whether we call it master or main. So when the racialized claims started over how calling the default branch in Git repositories &amp;quot;master&amp;quot; was PrObLEmAtIC, I thought, fine, what skin is it off anyone's or my back to change? If this is really important, can make a real difference, great. Let's do it. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;How naive.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;This was a classic exploit of good faith, and I fell for it.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Changing master to main changed less than nothing. Because nothing was or is ever enough in this arena. As soon as this word battle was won, it was just on to the next and the next (&lt;a href="https://itconnect.uw.edu/guides-by-topic/identity-diversity-inclusion/inclusive-language-guide/"&gt;and the next&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;But the upside of being hit by an exploit like this is that you eventually end up with a patch that closes the hole. And rest assured, this hole in our collective good faith is now closed. People are not going to be this gullible twice. I am not going to be this gullible twice. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;Next time the firewall will be ready.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>David Heinemeier Hansson</name>
      <email>dhh@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/36452</id>
    <published>2024-04-12T07:14:22Z</published>
    <updated>2024-04-12T07:14:22Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/imperfections-create-connections-bc87d630"/>
    <title>Imperfections create connections</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;The engine is in wrong place in a Porsche 911. It's hanging out the back, swinging the car like a pendulum. And that's key to why it's the most iconic sports car ever made. This fundamental imperfection is part of how it creates the connection.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;This is true of mechanical watches too. They're hilariously complicated pieces of engineering that tell time worse than a $20 Casio quartz watch. And that's why we love them. The imperfection of timekeeping, the need to manually wind the things, cements the connection.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;That's how computers used to feel too. The Amiga, and the Commodore 64 before it, were quirky bread boxes. Using chips named things like Agnus, Alice, Denise, Lisa, and Paula. With clicking, whirring disk drives. The flickering screen when software was loading. As distinctly different from the competition as a Porsche flat-six is from a Ferrari V12.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;But the quirky is almost all gone from modern day computers. The mac in particular has been massaged to within an inch of perfection, and has thus become harder to connect with. It's a curious contradiction. We strive to make things better and better, but if we succeed, we reminisce of the quirks that used to be.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;The last MacBook I really loved was the original 11&amp;quot; MacBook Air. It was full of compromises. A cramped screen. Chips that weren't quite fast enough. An iconic, wedgy design. It was so good because it was also kinda bad.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;I thought that era was simply gone. But over the last month or so, I've developed much of the same affection for the &lt;a href="https://frame.work/products/laptop-diy-13-gen-intel"&gt;Framework 13&lt;/a&gt;. Exactly because of all it's compromises and it's quirky design choices.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;It uses an odd 3:2 display, which is almost as tall as it is wide. In a time when most every other maker has gone 16:9 or 16:10. And it's matte, not glossy.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;The keyboard has twice the travel of most modern laptops. Giving it almost a vintage feel, which, once you get used to it, is really addictive.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;It has interchangeable ports?! You can configure the 4 slots with every combination of USB C, USB A, ethernet ports, HDMI ports, and additional storage you desire. Then swap them quickly and easily. An ingenious alternative to dongle life.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;And to top it off, I've chosen to run Linux on mine full time. I started out dual booting with Windows, but quickly realized that Linux ran faster on this AMD 7840U chip, and I found that Linux gave me everything I needed in more of that quirky style that gives the Framework machine its appeal in the first place.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Those are all the good parts, but there are plenty of drawbacks too. Compared to a modern MacBook, the battery is inferior. I got 6 hours in mixed use yesterday. The screen is only barely adequate to run at retina-like 2x for smooth looking fonts. Linux is far less polished than macOS. But somehow it just doesn't really matter.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;First of all, 6 hours is enough for regular use. If I'm doing more than that in a single stint without getting up, I'll be paying for it physically anyway. And the somewhat cramped resolution has made me fall in love with full-screen apps again, like I used to do with that 11&amp;quot; MacBook Air.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;But this is all picking at the parts when the grand story is the sum. This quirky, flawed machine has created a connection I haven't had with a piece of physical computer hardware in a very long time. That's notable!&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;I know this testimony isn't likely to appeal seriously to most mac users. Just like it wouldn't really have appealed to me a year or two ago. I just wasn't in the market for a change. And that's fine. Apple makes really, really good computers these days. Damn near perfect ones.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;And most people don't care that the 911 has the engine in the back. In fact, they don't care about cars at all, really. They just want to get from A to B, as quickly, cheaply, and smoothly as possible. And they tell time perfectly from their smart phone display. This is the democratization of progress. Wonderful.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;But if you're the kind of person who might appreciate a slightly notchy manual gearbox, the click of a mechanical shutter on a camera, the ticking of the escapement in a watch, or, dare I say it, putting on a vinyl record, you should checkout the Framework 13. The AMD version starts at just around a thousand bucks. So it's not like you have to switch your whole computing life around to give it a try.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;And, if you're a programmer, I think you should actually give Linux a try as well. I've smirked about &amp;quot;This Is The Year of Linux on the Desktop&amp;quot; for over twenty years, but now that I've been actually running it for over a month, I've realized it's actually here. And probably has been for quite a while. I just run Ubuntu 23.10, and together with &lt;a href="https://ulauncher.io/"&gt;ulauncher&lt;/a&gt; + &lt;a href="https://extensions.gnome.org/extension/4548/tactile/"&gt;tactile&lt;/a&gt;, it's a delightful desktop experience (see &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/dhh/159b129f511f76db3ae8adb463f70d05"&gt;my whole Ubuntu setup script&lt;/a&gt;). I even found a replacement for my beloved iA Writer in &lt;a href="https://typora.io/"&gt;Typora&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Make no mistake, there's more fuss. More snags, more imperfections. So if you go in expecting the same level of perfection you'd get from company worth three trillion, you might be disappointed. But if you consider this the work of a worldwide open source community, it's incredible how close it is in most areas, ahead in a few, and not that far behind in the rest.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Dare to add a little imperfection into your computing setup, and you might just find a deeper connection to the bits and electrons running it all. And if you don't, at least you got to see the sun rise in a fun location.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>David Heinemeier Hansson</name>
      <email>dhh@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/36432</id>
    <published>2024-04-11T09:04:00Z</published>
    <updated>2024-04-11T09:04:00Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/enough-problems-to-go-around-c10b887d"/>
    <title>Enough problems to go around</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;The worst kind of company is usually not the one where there's too much real work to do, but the kind where there's not enough. It's in this realm the real monsters appear. Without enough real problems to go around, humans are prone to invent fictitious and dreadful ones.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;This is the root of David Graeber's &lt;a href="https://strikemag.org/bullshit-jobs/"&gt;Bullshit Jobs&lt;/a&gt; analysis. That a shocking percentage of people work jobs that they themselves see little to no meaning in, because the work that's being produced makes no difference, has no essence. It's enough to make anyone mad.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;Now part of the problem is clearly one of perspective. I'm always amazed by the pride and duty it appears most Japanese workers put into the most mundane jobs. I forget where I read this, but it's the difference between being a happy zoo keeper who think of their job as &amp;quot;tending to the welfare of the elephants&amp;quot; rather than just &amp;quot;shoveling shit all day&amp;quot;.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;But it's not all subjective either. We are biologically tuned to conserve energy while being cognitively tuned to crave a challenge. So when the load is material, we often wish it was lighter. But if we actually succeed in lightening the load, we wonder why we're unhappy.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;This is one of those contradictory aspects of the human condition, and one that's foolish to attempt to resolve. The trick I've found is to believe both things to be true at the same time. Yes, occasionally there's a need to rest and conserve energy. But equally so, there's a need to get back into the arena, and wrestle with something significant. &lt;a href="https://signalvnoise.com/posts/1930-mojito-island-is-a-mirage"&gt;Mojito island&lt;/a&gt;, all the time, is a curse, not a blessing. &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;And in fact, it probably is worse, for most people, to have too many stretches of too little to do than the opposite. Tales of workers dropping dead a year into retirement is a common folklore expression of this knowledge. &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;All this to say: don't slice the few, meaningful problems you have at work too thin. The worst injury you can inflict on knowledge workers is leaving them with too little of consequence to contest with.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Meaningful problems are the most valuable human motivators. Made-up problems are a blight. Ensure you have not quite enough time and people available to tackle the former lest you start inventing the latter.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>David Heinemeier Hansson</name>
      <email>dhh@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/36417</id>
    <published>2024-04-10T08:41:25Z</published>
    <updated>2024-04-10T08:41:25Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/you-re-not-guaranteed-a-spot-on-the-team-95080248"/>
    <title>You're not guaranteed a spot on the team</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;I've always hated the saying &amp;quot;we're like family here&amp;quot; when it comes to work. Because it's obviously not true, and it's usually &lt;a href="https://signalvnoise.com/svn3/the-company-isnt-a-family/"&gt;cynically invoked by management&lt;/a&gt; to entice an undue obligation of sacrifice. Implying that you should give it all to The Company -- constantly working weekends, always being available on vacations, and all the rest -- but when the necessities of the business change, you'll realize the obligation was never truly mutual.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;So far, so agreeable to most people. They usually already have a family. They're not looking to supplant it with a fake corporate version. And they don't need to. Work can and should be friendly, fun, and rewarding without the blood relations.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;But if work is not a family, what is it then?&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;I think &lt;a href="https://jobs.netflix.com/culture#dream-team"&gt;Netflix got it right&lt;/a&gt;: it's a professional team. One where colleagues earn a spot by being really good in their given position. But also -- and this is the hard part! -- one where someone may fail to make the cut, if they aren't up to the standards of the team, don't fit in the given position, or simply hasn't been playing well enough for a while.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;You can't have it both ways. You can't scorn the use of &amp;quot;we're a family&amp;quot; and then also expect that colleagues who can't keep up are spared the cut. It's either or, if you're going to have a high-performing team.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Think of it this way. There are millions of people playing soccer in the world and having fun. There are probably thousands who play at some level of professionalism. But there are only 11 spots on the starting lineup of Manchester United. You can be very good at soccer, and still not be part of that lineup.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;Now the natural delusion of every business owner is to think that they're running Manchester United when in fact they're barely hanging on in third division. But the point is actually the same. Even in third division, there's a level of competence that makes someone a good fit. We can't all be the best. But there's room for almost anyone who's half-way decent to play (or work) productively SOMEWHERE.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;And the reality is that if someone is a fit for third division, they'd have a terrible time on that Manchester United starting lineup. The expectations would be sky high. The gaps in their competency would quickly and painfully be revealed. They'd soon realize they're in the wrong place. Cutting them from the team would be an act of mercy, not cruelty.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Note that it's more than fine to give someone who shows promise a chance in a position that seems like a stretch. But after a couple of games, the progress should be apparent. Either you're revealing the fact that they're quickly stepping up to the role or you're revealing the fact that they won't. Both are valuable learnings, but not if you squander the insight, and don't act accordingly. &lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;This is perhaps the most important job of the coach or manager. Knowing when to make the cut, and having the strength to do it. There'll always be a million reasons, especially if someone is well-liked, why you should wait longer, be more patient. But to do the job of being in charge well, you have to be decisive in face of incomplete evidence.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Not everyone is meant to be Messi or to play on his team. But we wouldn't have much of a sport if his level was the only level. Find your level, find a team that fits with it, and play to the best of your ability. That's the beautiful game.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>David Heinemeier Hansson</name>
      <email>dhh@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/36280</id>
    <published>2024-04-03T10:29:14Z</published>
    <updated>2024-04-03T10:29:14Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/le-mans-2024-1f87d732"/>
    <title>Le Mans 2024</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;This will be my 11th attempt. The first time I showed up on the grid at Le Mans was in 2012 -- some five years after I had first driven a real race car, and even less time since I made participating in the world's greatest endurance race the ultimate goal. But it almost didn't happen this year.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;See, motorsports relies on a curious mix of money and talent. It's usually not enough just to be good at driving to get a seat in a competitive car. The majority of teams competing, certainly in sports car racing, either are or have been funded by passionate privateers who bring the budget to make racing possible. Even in Formula 1 is this part of the dynamic.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;I bring some of the money and some of the talent, but never enough to single-handedly make a program worthy of a Le Mans entry happen. I have to team up with other drivers who bring another part of the budget, and a bit more talent, as well as some drivers who just bring their peak talent. Oh, and find a team that preferably has a few sponsors to close the gap. It's always a dance.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;And this year, it seemed like the dance wasn't going to close. Plenty of conversations, plenty of ideas, but no contract, no signatures. Until suddenly, a few weeks ago, a driver dropped out of their contract, and voila, a seat with Nielsen Racing for the European Le Mans Series and the 24 Hours of Le Mans was &lt;a href="https://sportscar365.com/lemans/elms/heinemeier-hansson-completes-nielsen-lmp2-lineup/"&gt;available for me&lt;/a&gt; to fill. Nice!&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;But it's a weird time in sports car racing. On the one hand, this will be perhaps the most exciting 24 Hours of Le Mans ever, in terms of high-profile manufacturer involvement. We'll see competition between Ferrari, Porsche, Lamborghini, Toyota, Cadillac, BMW, Peugeot, and Alpine this June in France. No wonder the race has been sold out since November.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;On the other hand, nobody seems to know what the future of the car is going to look like. Is everything going electric? Will AI be driving us all around shortly? Who's going to reap the spoils of this transformation: Software makers in Silicon Valley or battery makers in China? Where does this leave the historic motoring brands of Europe?&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;You'd think this level of uncertainty about the future would have dampened the will among car makers to spend lavishly on big-budget racing programs. And yet we're at an all-time high for both Formula 1 and sportscar racing. It's curious.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;Not that I'm complaining, mind you. It's rather amazing to be able to participate in such a golden era of motorsport. To be able to show up to the Super Bowl or Wimbledon or World Cup finals of our sport, as an amateur, and compete with the best drivers in the world. What a privilege.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;Even more so because I know this isn't going to last forever. I was 32 when I first drove at Le Mans. Now I'm 44. Drivers don't get better after forty, that's just a fact.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;Most have already retired by then, actually. Fernando Alonso, at 42, being the exception that proves the rule. So I keep waiting for my dip to come any minute now. For the lap times to fall off, first a little, then a lot. Or for the incident rate to increase. There's just no fighting nature, it will happen.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;But perhaps because I don't have that peak talent, I'll be spared a little longer. Be given a few more races at the top of my game, before the inevitable decline comes.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;I don't say that with any trepidation. I'm at peace with the circle of life, it's array of inevitable declines, and with it's finality. Nobody gets to be their best at almost anything forever, certainly not in the physical realm, and none of us will make it out of alive. If anything, there's a sense of relief in knowing that none of it -- not racing, not programming, not entrepreneurship -- is meant to go on forever.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Perhaps this is an easier existential pill to swallow once you've had kids. Seeing my three boys get quicker in their gokarts, whether they'll eventually turn it into car racing or not, tastes like the saying &amp;quot;when old men plant trees whose shade they know they shall never sit in&amp;quot;.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Now we're really off track, but that is perhaps one of the most rewarding aspects of having children. This biologically-infused acceptance of finality. I don't have to live forever, because the human lineage I'm a part of, and that's millions of years old, is going to continue. Whether they'll be racing cars or not.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;But that brings us back to one of my favorite parts about driving a race car real fast: There's no time for existential deliberation! All your attention must be focused on making the perfect inputs for the next corner, lest you give up a tenth of a second or make a mistake that sends you and the car into the wall. Everything else simply must vanish for your attention to be devoted to the task at hand: Go fast, don't crash.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.24h-lemans.com/en"&gt;June 14-16&lt;/a&gt;, then. For 24 hours. Zoom, zoom.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>David Heinemeier Hansson</name>
      <email>dhh@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/36232</id>
    <published>2024-03-31T19:05:58Z</published>
    <updated>2024-03-31T19:05:58Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/bad-therapy-08849dc9"/>
    <title>Bad Therapy</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Bad-Therapy-Kids-Arent-Growing/dp/0593542924/"&gt;This book nails it&lt;/a&gt;. What it's like to be a parent with school-age children in America right now. So many kids with a diagnosis of one sort or another, so much monitoring of children's every move, so much anxiety over the most trivial things, like the sugar content of a cupcake. Abigail Shrier ties all these threads together into a damning tapestry of well-cited arguments for why much of modern parenting in America is failing the kids it purports to care for so catastrophically.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;I simply couldn't put it down. I've read a few parenting books, and I usually have to somewhat dig to find something to take away. But Bad Therapy required no digging. It is unusually dense with eye-opening and deeply resonating take-aways. From its diagnosis to its anecdotes.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's also depressing. That this is what's become of the modern American childhood experience in so many places. The almost fully eroded sense of childhood independence, with its moderate dangers and teaching moments. Replaced with cotton-ball cocoons to keep kids from dealing with even the most minor of setbacks themselves. Lest accusations start flying of how somebody, somewhere OUGHT TO HAVE DONE SOMETHING.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's without a doubt the worst thing about living in America for me at the moment. The hyper-active, hyper-involved parents who have hair-trigger intervention fingers ready to be pulled at the slightest appearance of social discomfort or disharmony. Eager to do calls, follow-ups, and long threads of texting to &amp;quot;unpack&amp;quot; whatever happened between so and so in the playground at recess. Placated by administrators and teachers all to eager to assume greater involvement with every living millisecond and millimeter of school life.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Combined with the fact that we, me, us are all complicit. All so easily sucked into it all. I hate it.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Which is how Shrier's book emerges like such an oasis in the middle of a desert of such arid ideas. From &amp;quot;gentle parenting&amp;quot;, to social-emotional-learning programs, to trauma-me-this-and-trauma-me-that thinking, it's all seemingly spreading everywhere. So this forceful refutation of the lot of it quenches a deep thirst for opposition. And boy does it deliver!&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;It's delightfully polemic, with pointed and named refutations of the specific intellectuals who are at the center of advancing these bad ideas. It reads like it was written by a writer entirely unafraid of slaughtering the sacred cows of the upper-class zeitgeist. Because it is! &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;In 2020, Shrier wrote &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Irreversible-Damage-Transgender-Seducing-Daughters/dp/1684510317"&gt;Irreversible Damage&lt;/a&gt;, about the dramatic surge in transgender identification, and the medical interventions and experiments that have come with it. It was so controversial that it made one of the leading lawyers at the ACLU, Chase Strangio, tweet that &amp;quot;stopping the circulation of this book and these ideas is 100% a hill I will die on&amp;quot;. Yikes.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;br&gt;So to say Shrier has been through the cancellation ringer is an understatement of epic proportions. Her &lt;a href="https://open.spotify.com/episode/4SIh4Pt39AtGQYzMJMNkv1"&gt;first appearance on Joe Rogan's podcast&lt;/a&gt; even prompted a fringe of Spotify employees to protest the company's sponsorship of the podcast.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;But Shrier made it through. And there is perhaps nothing quite as fortifying as staring down a censorship mob, and then later seeing your testimony confirmed. See &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2024/mar/09/disturbing-leaks-from-us-gender-group-wpath-ring-alarm-bells-in-nhs"&gt;the WPATH Files&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/health-68549091"&gt;the NHS' reversal on puberty blockers&lt;/a&gt;, as just two examples validating the concerns raised in that book.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;No wonder Bad Therapy has instantly become a best seller. Regardless of your parenting approach, I think you'll be forced to think long and hard about it after reading Shrier's book. It's all but ensured to push some buttons in almost everyone. When it does, don't quit it, stick with it.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;The message couldn't be more timely. The mental health statistics on kids and young adults today are horrifying. What American parents have been doing for the last twenty-plus years is so resoundingly not working. All the therapy, the accommodations, the pills, and the interventions have failed to produce a generation of happy, independent kids. It's way over due for thee parents, us parents, to go back to drawing board. There's no way the answer is more of the same.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;You gotta read it.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>David Heinemeier Hansson</name>
      <email>dhh@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/35918</id>
    <published>2024-03-15T17:24:00Z</published>
    <updated>2024-04-10T15:56:56Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/chart-the-course-set-the-pace-hold-the-line-0f3ea916"/>
    <title>Chart the course, set the pace, hold the line</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;I break the essential responsibilities of the company executive into three distinct buckets. They are:&lt;br&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;h1&gt;1. Chart the course&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;div&gt;Where are we going? What are we building? Who is it for? Any executive running anything has to know the answer to these questions in order to lead anyone anywhere. If you don't have a clue where you're going, any road can take you there, and running in circles is as good as making progress. This is not viable.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt;That doesn't mean having a five-year plan! Or even a quarterly target! We decide on what features we're going to build for &lt;a href="https://basecamp.com/"&gt;Basecamp&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.hey.com/"&gt;HEY&lt;/a&gt; every 6-8 weeks. That's charting the course just in time and at a high resolution.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt;Because if anything, being a &amp;quot;long-term thinker&amp;quot; is an invitation to smell your own intellectual exhaust fumes. It's much easier to bullshit from 30,000 ft than it is when imminent decisions stare you in the face.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt;And someone's has to do it! Someone has to say: This is what we're doing. Let's go.&lt;br&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;h1&gt;2. Set the pace&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;div&gt;Not only does work easily expand to fit the time allotted, but our ambitions will shrink along with our declining productivity. The slower you're moving, the less you think you can do, the slower you're moving. The only counter to this is to be ambitious, bold, and impatient.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt;Again, this doesn't mean cracking the whip over a herd of cubicled programmers zombieing their way through yet another death march day on a 12-hour shift. Setting the pace isn't about demanding more hours, it's about demanding more &lt;em&gt;from&lt;/em&gt; those hours.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; It's also about constantly questioning the premise of the work. Why are we doing it this way? Could it be done differently? Are you prepping for contingencies that are too remote to matter? Or are you not spending enough time where it really counts?&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; The only way to tell is by knowing the work. Executives who drift high up in the clouds have a hard time seeing the terrain. You can only get so much information second-hand or from outdated maps. You have to be there to know.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; So to be bold, you must have insight – or you're just delusional. Credibility is built on pushing for a reach and then actually making it. If you're constantly pushing for the impossible, and none of it happens, you're a clown. Get out of here.&lt;br&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;h1&gt;3. Hold the line&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;div&gt;Quality withers quickly when nobody sweats it. You have to take it personal, to some degree. It has to offend your sensibilities when things are not right, to some degree. Because you need that energy to halt the work and redo what isn't right when you find out. If you let it slide, if you don't sweat, eventually nobody else will.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt;And holding the line on quality isn't just about the customer experience, it's about everything. It's about writing code that'll be a joy to read in three years. It's about giving support staff enough policy leeway to deal with problems (without giving the farm away). It's about making sure none of the writing that's signed by the company makes you cringe.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt;Holding the line also means being willing to pay for it. Always look for a good bargain, when good quality is available at a great price, but never be cheap. You're holding the line so you'll be able to be proud of what you're producing tomorrow, next year, next decade. A culture of quality is built one product and process decision at a time.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt;Do all these three things well, do them consistently, do them when it's hard, do them when it doesn't look like it's working, and regardless of what happens, you'll have done your best with what was there. Whether that's enough for success or sustainability is usually out of your hands anyway. But great execution according to these three responsibilities have a way of finding the gold.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>David Heinemeier Hansson</name>
      <email>dhh@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/35906</id>
    <published>2024-03-15T01:17:38Z</published>
    <updated>2024-03-15T16:42:23Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/beware-the-leviathans-56db3d48"/>
    <title>Beware the leviathans</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;I've been &lt;a href="https://signalvnoise.com/svn3/testimony-before-the-house-antitrust-subcommittee/"&gt;pleading&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://signalvnoise.com/svn3/testimony-before-the-north-dakota-senate-industry-business-and-labor-committee/"&gt;with&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/testimony-before-the-arizona-house-of-representatives-e48f3e89"&gt;antitrust&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://signalvnoise.com/svn3/on-apples-monopoly-power-to-destroy-hey/"&gt;authorities&lt;/a&gt; around the world to do something about Big Tech for years now. Especially with those awful app store monopolies that have been choking out developers left, right, and center. But now that &lt;a href="https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2024/01/apple-announces-changes-to-ios-safari-and-the-app-store-in-the-european-union/"&gt;something&lt;/a&gt; finally looks to be happening, I'm suddenly concerned that it might, and that we'll end up wishing that it didn't.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; It's not because I suddenly have a newfound appreciation for Apple's or Google's right to milk their mobile tollbooths for billions more. Au contraire. My concern is rather that the sovereign leviathans of the world, be it the EU or the US, might not exactly share as many interests with free market advocates as it appears on the surface.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; Let's start with the Digital Markets Act. That's the main antitrust battering ram hitting the gates of Apple's keep at the moment. And Apple doesn't seem to know what's up, down, or any which way around. They're stumbling from &lt;a href="https://www.theregister.com/2024/03/02/apple_reverses_pwa_decision/"&gt;one defiant defeat&lt;/a&gt; to &lt;a href="https://techcrunch.com/2024/03/12/apple-to-allow-web-distribution-for-ios-apps-in-latest-dma-tweaks/"&gt;the next humiliating flip-flop&lt;/a&gt; on policy. It's hard not to be filled with schadenfreude in response.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; Apple is finally getting a dose of its own infuriating medicine! It's fumbling in the dark trying to comply with vague, ambiguous rules that seem designed for maximum frustration. And it can't seem to get a straight answer from said authorities on exactly what it'll take to be legal. It has to invent a myriad of APIs and policies up front, only then to be told what will be accepted (or not) after the fact.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; Welcome to &lt;a href="https://www.hey.com/apple/"&gt;our world&lt;/a&gt;, Apple. This is exactly what it feels like to be a developer knocking on the door of your app store bureaucracy. Being bandied about from reviewer to reviewer, never certain what it takes to make you happy. Constantly wishing that the next update will just make your bureaucrats go away and leave us alone.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; But once I've let the dark delight subside, I must return to my principles. The reason developers are so frustrated with the app store monopolies is exactly the absence of clear rules that are consistently and predictably enforced. We want a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magna_Carta"&gt;rule of law&lt;/a&gt; where it's obvious what's kosher and what's not. Where everyone is treated the same, regardless of industry, power, or privilege. A lady justice blind to her subjects.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; In the best case scenario, this awful DMA adventure that Apple is currently struggling through will be a mirror for the company to reflect on its own behavior. And, having felt exactly that sense of intolerable frustration shared by countless developers, they'll use the introspection to reconsider their extractive ways.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; Yes, that's very much wishful thinking. But I refuse to stop hoping, because if you give up on hope, you're bound to become cynical, and that's a curse worse than any commercial dispossession.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; But let's return to the biggest potential threat here. Not from Apple, not from Google, but from the sovereign leviathans. The legislatures, the courts, and the rest of the governmental machinery slowly churning their big grinding gears in the US and the EU.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; The DMA is convoluted and complicated because the EU is trying to have its cake and eat it too. It purports to open markets and ensure competition, but at the same time embrace the power of consolidation by co-opting Apple's (and Google's) reach and gatekeeper privileges. This latter motive is what governments on both sides of the Atlantic have been pursuing for the internet since day one. To bring it under their control.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; You see this with the scarily &lt;a href="https://www.legaldive.com/news/digital-services-act-dsa-eu-misinformation-law-propaganda-compliance-facebook-gdpr/691657/"&gt;authoritarian laws targeting &amp;quot;misinformation&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.ctvnews.ca/politics/government-says-only-extreme-online-hate-speech-would-be-probed-by-human-rights-body-1.6797025"&gt;other forms of speech&lt;/a&gt; that are spreading in both the new world and the old. You see it in the countless of examples of overt collaboration between the key platforms and government censors. &lt;a href="https://twitterfiles.substack.com/p/the-censorship-industrial-complex"&gt;The Twitter Files&lt;/a&gt; gave us a depressing look into how officials were circumventing the first amendment in the US, and most of the rest of the world doesn't even have a right to free speech enshrined in their constitution. So laws that seek increasingly draconian penalties for forbidden speech are coming out of the woodwork everywhere.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; And here's the kicker. These laws need implementation, and no process has proven more effective than deputizing the likes of Apple, Google, Amazon, and other Big Tech platform owners. Making them responsible for carrying out the censorship. Whether that takes the explicit form of official laws and their invocation, like the dystopian financial crackdown on &lt;a href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/go-truck-yourself-a14306d9"&gt;the Canadian trucker protests&lt;/a&gt; and their donors, or the &lt;a href="https://www.foxnews.com/media/parler-ceo-blasts-aoc-elected-officials-who-called-to-ban-his-app-i-think-its-sick"&gt;threats&lt;/a&gt; from officials that &lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/01/10/technology/parler-app-trump-free-speech.html"&gt;pushed Parlor off the internet&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; Now I know that as soon as we dive into the specifics, like the Canadian trucker protests or Parlor or anything else from those divisive archives, this whole debate turns into a partisan team sport. Whatever lofty principles people hold in the abstract are quickly sacrificed, if there's a chance to score a win against the opposing side. This is when labels fly freely, and suddenly everyone is a nazi or a communist.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; But whatever side you're on (or whether you take a side at all!), you ought to recognize that the rings of power usually change side every now and then. Every overreach you find justified when its your team wielding the advantage is one you'll rue when it's turned back against you.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; I think even the most hardcore partisans actually know this, even if they're loathe to admit it. It's why you have a parade of Democrats in the US chasing Trump with every bogus legal claim under the sun while fretting that he'll &amp;quot;weaponize the courts to pursue his political enemies&amp;quot;, if he wins this November. Pots and kettles, all black.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; (Yes, again, I recognize that mentioning Trump will completely shut off the frontal lobes of half the audience, if references to Canadian truckers or Parlor didn't do the job already. But the hypocrisy is just too grand to ignore. Regardless of whether you think Trump is a once-in-a-century villain or not.)&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; All this is why reasonable people might well just &lt;a href="https://x.com/DavidSacks/status/1768071968962806271?s=20"&gt;have second thoughts&lt;/a&gt; about whether the US government should ban TikTok. I think there are plenty of valid reasons, most persuasively those on reciprocal trade, but let's not pretend the slippery slope hasn't been proven right repeatedly in the last few years.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; Emergency powers invoked when honking horns got too much. Misinformation missions expanding to include malinformation too (true information that's unhelpful/damaging to the cause/narrative). Political opponents labeled as traitors and in cahoots with foreign adversaries.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; I think it's perfectly reasonable to worry how a ban/forced sale of TikTok might pave the way for similar actions against &lt;a href="https://x.com/DavidSacks/status/1768147618000167093?s=20"&gt;X&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="https://x.com/DavidSacks/status/1768148314359554067?s=20"&gt;Rumble&lt;/a&gt; or whoever fails to kick off people saying the wrong words.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; That's the context in which I worry about what comes next in the fight against Big Tech monopolies. A future where this intolerable concentration of power is not so much disbanded as simply subsumed into the growing arsenal of oppressive powers that are increasingly being collected by Western democracies. All in the name of fighting the ever-expanding list of forbidden words and &lt;a href="https://www.justthefacts.media/p/criminalizing-free-speech-the-pfizer"&gt;topics&lt;/a&gt;, amongst other boogeymen.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; I want to see the monopolies of Apple and Google addressed. And I also think the leviathans are our best bet in the short term, but I'm open to the idea that the short term isn't worth selling out our principles for in the long term. That maybe we ought to place our faith in &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mScpHTIi-kM"&gt;iterative game theory&lt;/a&gt;, and the fact that critical platforms do change, albeit rarely and slowly.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; There's one version of history that holds that it was the Justice Departments case against Microsoft that opened up the tech world to new entrants in the early 2000s. That without their intervention, we'd been doomed to live with the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet_Explorer_5"&gt;awfulness of IE&lt;/a&gt; forever, and Windows would have reigned supreme until the end of our days.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; But there's another version that sees the inherently disruptive force of the internet, the rise of Firefox, then Chrome, together with Google, Facebook, and the rest of that eras challenges to Microsoft, as happening without the intervention of the leviathan. And that those same forces, and the nature of playing successive rounds of the prisoner's dilemma, is &lt;a href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/microsoft-taught-apple-nothing-592d398d"&gt;what lead Microsoft to lose the ultimate prize&lt;/a&gt; on the next decades: mobile.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; Usually, I find it relatively easy to navigate such questions and counterfactuals to arrive at a position worth going all-in on. But not this time. This time I'll admit to be equally concerned with whether the EU, to take the DMA specifically, is successful or not.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; In the end, we might all come to echo &lt;a href="https://www.goodreads.com/quotes/7141047-marry-and-you-will-regret-it-don-t-marry-you-will"&gt;Kierkegaard's immortal sense of regret&lt;/a&gt;: Tackle Big Tech, and you will regret it. Don't tackle Big Tech, and you will regret that too. Either way, you will regret it.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; Oy.&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>David Heinemeier Hansson</name>
      <email>dhh@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <id>tag:world.hey.com,2005:World::Post/35881</id>
    <published>2024-03-13T20:37:56Z</published>
    <updated>2024-03-13T20:37:56Z</updated>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://world.hey.com/dhh/developers-are-on-edge-4dfcf9c1"/>
    <title>Developers are on edge</title>
    <content type="html">&lt;div class="trix-content"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;It's a double whammy of anxiety for developers at the moment. On the one hand, &lt;a href="https://layoffs.fyi/"&gt;the layoffs are dragging on&lt;/a&gt;. The industry has shed more jobs in a shorter period than any time since the dot-com bust over twenty years ago. Seasoned veterans who used to have recruiters banging on their door nonstop &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/Carnage4Life/status/1767527635297722786"&gt;can suddenly barely get a callback&lt;/a&gt;. And now the threat of AI suddenly got even more urgent and imminent with &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/cognition_labs/status/1767548763134964000"&gt;the launch of Devin&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; If you zoom out, though, developers are still flying high on tailwinds that took them to the moon over the past decade. Yes, hundreds of thousands of people have lost their jobs in the tech industry, but the preceding hiring bonanza still leaves us with an enormous and wealthy industry. And the wage gains secured during the go-go days are still massive, despite what inflation has eroded over the last few years. Contrast the fortunes of premium programmers in 2024 with their situation from 2014 or 2008, and they're still looking mighty privileged.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; But humans don't react to absolute status or wealth. All the anxiety or exhilaration is in the delta. Are we moving up or down? Forwards or backwards? And right now, except for a tiny group of gilded AI wizards, most programmers have either seen their prospects stalled or become more precarious. So yesterday's wins are quickly pushed aside by tomorrow's worries.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; There's some irony in this change of fortune. Programmers, as a group, have prospered tremendously by automating other people's jobs over the past half century. But when it's other people's livelihoods, we naturally have a much easier time seeing the big picture. That the aggregate prosperity of the world improves as productivity goes up. It's a little harder when it's your own profession feeling the pressure.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; It's hard to tell how real that pressure actually is, though. Okay, the layoffs are indisputable, and the tough hiring environment an inevitable consequence. But the wreckage of the dot-com bust was cleared in a few short years, and then it was back to full steam ahead. And exuberant tech analysts told cabbies in 2017 that self-driving cars were going to put them all out of a job in a hot minute. That still hasn't happened either.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; That's the trouble with The Future. It's awfully difficult to predict when it'll actually arrive. All we're doing is making bets and taking guesses. &lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; My guess would be that just like agriculture went from requiring the participation of 97% of the world's population in the age of subsistence farming to the mere 2% required for our industrial processes today, so too will go the way of the programmer.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; That is, I do think we've &lt;em&gt;probably&lt;/em&gt; seen the high-water mark of the manual programmer. That maybe our industry and employment charts might look like the Tokyo stock market when we look back from the future. Sideways &lt;a href="https://www.macrotrends.net/2593/nikkei-225-index-historical-chart-data"&gt;since the 90s&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; Now that still leaves an enormous industry with plenty of prospects, of course. If anything, AI is likely going to make the tech industry even more integrated in society and thus more valuable. But we just might not need as many human programmers pounding code with their little meat fingers. Just like the aggregate value of the agricultural industry has gone up a lot since the pre-industrial era, even if the number of hands in the field have shrunk to almost nothing.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; So while it's hard to do, it's useless to worry. The Future is out of your hands and out of your control. No profession has ever successfully resisted automation or redundancy in the face of technological advancement over the long term. Screaming at Devin will only distract you from enjoying the last glorious years of a golden run.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt; C'est la vie!&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content>
    <author>
      <name>David Heinemeier Hansson</name>
      <email>dhh@hey.com</email>
    </author>
  </entry>
</feed>
